<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Prison thoughts written by Tho. Browning, citiyen [sic] and cook of London, who hath been a prisoner in Ludgate ever since the twelveth day of August, 1680.</title>
            <author>Browning, Tho. (Thomas)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 137 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29888</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5188</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37167</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16263627</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16263627</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105161</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29888)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105161)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1089:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Prison thoughts written by Tho. Browning, citiyen [sic] and cook of London, who hath been a prisoner in Ludgate ever since the twelveth day of August, 1680.</title>
                  <author>Browning, Tho. (Thomas)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>52 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by the author in Ludgate (who is still a prisoner there),</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London  :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>English letters.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105161:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Priſon Thoughts,</hi> WRITTEN BY Tho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Browning CITIYEN AND COOK OF LONDON.</p>
            <p>Who hath been a <hi>PRISONER</hi> in <hi>Ludgate,</hi> ever ſince the <hi>Twelveth</hi> day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1680.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Dum Spiro, Spero; in Deum, Adjutorem meum.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed, and are to be Sold by the Author, in <hi>Ludgate</hi> (who is ſtill a Priſoner there.) <hi>Anno</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:105161:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:105161:2"/>
            <head>To the Worſhipful <hi>Geo. Daſhwood,</hi> Eſq Dame <hi>Margeret</hi> his Wife, the Lady <hi>Elizabeth Hare</hi> their Daughter; <hi>John Pery,</hi> Eſq Mrs. <hi>Katherine Browning</hi> my Wife, where ever ſhe is, and to all that are related to their Families, Grace and Peace.</head>
            <p>NOtwithſtanding my many great Troubles, I have had ſome retired Thoughts in my <hi>Adoleſcens,</hi> which are here brought to publick View, and do deſire you to Patronize the ſame. If you and others ſhall find ſuch benefit by reading them, as I have done by writing the ſame, my ends are anſwered. Time was, when I had no Thoughts of putting my ſelf in Print, but, <hi>Neceſſitas non habet Legem.</hi> Theſe are my firſt Fruits as an Offering to the World, which pray ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept. I do intend another ſuddenly, which perhaps may be more acceptable, and ſell better than this. My weak Endeavours ſhall not be any whit wanting therein.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Who am Your Moſt Humble and Obedient Servant in the Lord,</hi> Thomas Browning.</signed> Noſſe Teipſum. Vivat Rex, Curret Lex, Floret Grex. Finis Coronat Opus.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:105161:3"/>
            <head>A Coppy of a Letter ſent to my Wife;</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Admiration,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN my Fifty Eighth Letter I ſent you ſome Verſes, and this is my Fifty Ninth, where you may find an Epiſtle, which pray peruſe. It is in vain to expect any Approbation from you, having never yet received one Line in Writing from your Hand. And perceiving that you are reſolved nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſee, nor ſend to me, I do think that this may be the laſt time that I may trouble you in Writing: only remember that you have abuſed, neglected, ſlighted, and robbed a moſt Indulgent and loving Husband; for which I pray God to give you a hearty Repentance, before it be too late, and there be no meanes left to help your ſelf; as likewiſe all thoſe who have unlawfully, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry malitiouſly adviſed againſt me without any Cauſe. And if you, or they have any Pretences, I do hereby dare either to make them known to me, or the World; aſſuring that mine ſhall ſhortly be made known in Print, with as much Severity as Truth will bear, who am ſtill you Loving, though moſt Abuſed Husband,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Browning.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:105161:3"/>
            <head>Priſon Thoughts, &amp;c,</head>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <hi>OH deſpiſed, deſpiſed, deſpiſed; rejected, rejected, rejected, and Deſtroyed by you, my own Dear Wife, whoſe Name is</hi> Katherine Browning; <hi>I pitty, I pitty, I pitty, and ſhall not ceaſe Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for you Day and Night, that you may be converted: when you hear of</hi> Brownings <hi>Death, occaſioned by your meanes, you may ſhed a tear for him, if there be any Grace in you; none ought to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe their own Fleſh;</hi> Whom God hath Joyned together, let none put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: <hi>And if you had not gone from me, you might have been Miſtriſs of our Company; they have choſen an old Maſter this year in my ſtead. Take heed of theſe dreadful Sentences:</hi> You that are filthy, be filthy ſtill. There remains no more Sacrifice for Sin, but a fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful looking for of Judgment, Fiery Indignation, and fierce Anger of the Lord: <hi>with a,</hi> Go ye Curſed into Everlaſting Fire, prepared for Divels and Damn'd Spirits. <hi>From which Place, Good Lord deliver us. My Epiſtle begins:</hi> Few and evil have been the days of my Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage, I have had for Inheritance the Months of Vanity, and pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Nights have been appointed unto me; and do know that hereafter is laid up for me a Crown of Righteouſineſs, and not for me only, but for all them who love the appearance of the Lord Jeſus: Therefore all the days of my Life will I wait as a <hi>Hireling</hi> till my Change ſhall come. For I deſire to be Diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt, and do long to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move out of the Body, to dwell with the Lord; For I do know that if this Earthly Houſe of my Tabernacle were deſtroyed, I have a Bulilding given of God, that is a Houſe not made with Hands, but Eternal in the Heavens: Therefore I ſigh, deſiring to be cloathed with my Houſe which is from Heaven: and I do heartily look for, and do hope, that in noth ng I ſhall be aſhamed, but that with all confidence Chriſt ſhall be magnified in my Body, whether it be by Life or Death, for whither I live, it is to the Lord, or whether I die, it is to the Lord, therefore whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I live or die, I am the Lords. To Him therefore be Praiſe and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for evermore. I have fought a good Fight, I have kept the Faith,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105161:4"/>and do know in whom I have Believed, and am perſwaded that he is able to keep that which I have committed to his Charge: Againſt that Day, the Lord will quicken my mortal Body, and make it like to his own Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Body: Yea, though after my Skin, Worms deſtroy this Body, yet I ſhall ſee God in my Fleſh, whom I my ſelf ſhall ſee, and mine Eyes ſhall behold, and none other for me, though my Reins be conſumed within me, therefore I willingly lay down my Life, and commit my Soul unto God, as unto my faithful Creator. How excellent is thy Mercy, O God, therefore do I truſt under the Shadow of thy Wings. O bleſſed is the man whom thou doſt chooſe, and cauſeſt to come unto thee; he ſhall dwell in thy Courts, and ſhall be ſatisfied with the Pleaſures of thine Houſe, even of thy Holy Temple, thou ſhalt give him drink out of the Rivers of thy Pleaſures; for with thee is the Well of Life, and in thy Light ſhall we ſee Light; ſend me therefore thy Light and thy Truth, and let thy good Spirit lead me unto the Land of Righteouſneſs. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry me, O Lord, by thy Mercy, and bring me in thy Strength to thy Holy Habitation. Plant me in the Mountain of thine Inheritance, even in the Place which thou haſt prepared, and the Sanctuary which thou haſt Eſtabliſhed, that I may ſee the Goodneſs of the Lord in the Land of the Living. Let me behold thy Face in Righteouſneſs, and let me be ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with thine Image, for in thy Preſence is the Fulneſs of Joy, and at thy right Hand are Pleaſures for evermore: Into thy Hands, O Lord, I commend my Spirit, for thou haſt Redeemed it, O Lord God of Truth. Lord Jeſus receive my Spirit. The end of the upright man is Peace. As many as walk according to this Rule, Peace ſhall be upon them, and upon the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God. Now unto Him that is able to keep us, that we fall not, and to preſent us faultleſs before the Preſence of his Glory with Joy, to God only-wiſe be Glory, Majeſty, Dominion, and Power, both now and ever, ever, ever, Amen.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Ludgate,</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>The 12</hi>th <hi>of April, 1682.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poems">
               <head>
                  <hi>For my moſt Eſteemed Miſtriſs</hi> Katherine Browning, <hi>Theſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>This was ſent to her Aunt Madam</hi> Margaret Daſhwood <hi>by the hand of Mr. <hi>Joſeph Steed,</hi> her Nephew, to be conveyed as is Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected.</hi>
               </head>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:105161:4"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>SHall there be nothing left me but a Grave?</l>
                  <l>Shall I at laſt no other Dwelling have?</l>
                  <l>Oh let not Fleſh and Blood take note of this,</l>
                  <l>For if She do, 'twill poiſon all her Bliſs.</l>
                  <l>Could She but meditate on ſuch a thing,</l>
                  <l>She would have little cauſe to laugh or ſing;</l>
                  <l>It is a Death to her to think of Death,</l>
                  <l>How ſhe ſhall rot, and looſe her loved Breath.</l>
                  <l>Yet the great <hi>Jew</hi> that wiſely could diſcrie</l>
                  <l>What things were not, and what were vanity,</l>
                  <l>What pleaſed the Soul, and what the Fleſh did pain,</l>
                  <l>Did never think the thought of this was vain.</l>
                  <l>Then let my Soul, though Fleſh and Blood, repine,</l>
                  <l>Ponder on that, ſhall make them both Divine;</l>
                  <l>But why, O fooliſh Fleſh, ſhak'ſt thou at this,</l>
                  <l>Shrink'ſt thou from that which thy beſt Phyſick is,</l>
                  <l>Thou art Earth born, from it thou didſt deſcend,</l>
                  <l>And here grown Sick, thou canſt not eaſily mend,</l>
                  <l>Till t'ward thy Native Countrey thou repair;</l>
                  <l>And draw thy Meditations that cold Air.</l>
                  <l>Change but this Air, and think upon thy End,</l>
                  <l>Thy Sin will leſſen, and thy Soul will mend.</l>
                  <l>For as at Sea, when Clouds put out the Stars,</l>
                  <l>When Winds from Heaven, and Waves from Earth make Wars,</l>
                  <l>And mad brain'd Sailers all the Decks o're whelm,</l>
                  <l>The Pilate ſadly ſitting at the Helm,</l>
                  <l>Better directs the Ship where it ſhould go,</l>
                  <l>Than all their wild Endeavours can: even ſo</l>
                  <l>When through the Worlds dark Storms we ſend,</l>
                  <l>One quiet Pilot ſitting at the End:</l>
                  <l>One thought of Death our Courſe more right doth guide,</l>
                  <l>Than all the vain Works of our Life beſide.</l>
                  <l>Theſe thoughts will make thoſe which our Souls blood quaff,</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Horſeleeches</hi> ſtrow'd ore with Duſt, fall off.</l>
                  <l>If then to think of Death be ſo, Oh why</l>
                  <l>Should any think it is not good to die?</l>
                  <l>That of all things that Mortals fear and ſhun,</l>
                  <l>Doth hurt or grieve us leaſt when it is done:</l>
                  <l>This it the Port, this is Sins perfect Cure,</l>
                  <l>Till our Grave cover us, we ne're are ſure<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:105161:5"/>
                  <l>This only laſt remains, thither let's haſt,</l>
                  <l>Since Fleſh and Blood ſtill longs to know what's laſt:</l>
                  <l>It ever hath belong'd to Mortal Wights,</l>
                  <l>That ſeveral Heads take ſeveral Delights,</l>
                  <l>Some unto good, and ſome to bad have will,</l>
                  <l>But leaving that which I delight in: ill.</l>
                  <l>I joy in three which few can diſcommend,</l>
                  <l>And moſt deſire next to a conſtant Friend;</l>
                  <l>And theſe are they that draw me moſt along,</l>
                  <l>A <hi>well writ Book,</hi> a <hi>Picture,</hi> and a <hi>Song;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But as for Wealth, in which moſt take delight,</l>
                  <l>I get it not, nor of it do I write;</l>
                  <l>But of thoſe things endeavour brought me to,</l>
                  <l>I ſomewhat know, and ſomewhat I can do,</l>
                  <l>And theſe I love, and they do love to be</l>
                  <l>With ſuch as love and ſeek their company:</l>
                  <l>But will they ſtay with me, Oh no, alas,</l>
                  <l>They were belov'd long time before I was:</l>
                  <l>And when their Lovers died, they'd ſhroud and ſpread,</l>
                  <l>Nor will they go with me when I am dead:</l>
                  <l>Some Learned Friend perhaps may on my Herſe</l>
                  <l>Scatter ſome Lines, and ſtrew the Cloth with Verſe;</l>
                  <l>Painting perchance may gild ſome Flag or Banner,</l>
                  <l>And ſtick it on my Coffin for mine Honour;</l>
                  <l>Muſick may ſing my Dirge, and tell all Ears</l>
                  <l>I lov'd that Art which now their Sences hears.</l>
                  <l>And when 'tis done, and I no more can have,</l>
                  <l>Nothing will tarry with me but the Grave:</l>
                  <l>And 'tis moſt juſt, for here I did receive them,</l>
                  <l>I found them when I came, and here I leave them.</l>
                  <l>But will the things I want, and others have</l>
                  <l>Accompany their Owners to the Grave?</l>
                  <l>Will Beauty go; and ſtrength in Death appear,</l>
                  <l>Will Honour, or proud Riches tarry there?</l>
                  <l>They all ſay, nay, for let grim Death draw near,</l>
                  <l>Beauty looks pale, and Strength doth faint for fear:</l>
                  <l>Ther's little Luſt or Pride in naked Bones,</l>
                  <l>And Honour ſits on Cuſhions, not cold Stones;</l>
                  <l>Nay, ask our Friends, that when we are in Health,</l>
                  <l>Would die for love of us, or for our Wealth.</l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:105161:5"/>
                  <l>Mark what they ſet their Hands to, view it well,</l>
                  <l>Your Friend till Death, but once being dead, fare well.</l>
                  <l>Nought then will tarry but the Grave, for note,</l>
                  <l>How of a man new dead men talk by Rote;</l>
                  <l>This was his Wife, ſaith one, this was his Land.</l>
                  <l>This was his Friend, that was his Building, and</l>
                  <l>This was his Wealth, that his chiefeſt Bliſs,</l>
                  <l>And thus they talk a while of what was his:</l>
                  <l>But walk the Church-yard, and thou ſhalt have</l>
                  <l>Report, till Dooms-day, ſay, this is his Grave:</l>
                  <l>If Kings and Queens then can no more procure,</l>
                  <l>Nought but my Grave will tarry with me ſure.</l>
                  <l>Why therefore ſhould I ſtrive to get ſuch Things.</l>
                  <l>Since what the World contains no Surety brings,</l>
                  <l>Like men that claſp at Spirits, catch the Air,</l>
                  <l>So while we look after the things ſeem fair,</l>
                  <l>And gripe at all the World to ſerve our Luſt,</l>
                  <l>It through our Fingers ſlips, and leaves but duſt;</l>
                  <l>Yet ſtill the nearer Death we grow in Years,</l>
                  <l>This ſcraping Humour in us more appears,</l>
                  <l>And drowns not till we ſink, ſo muſt it be,</l>
                  <l>For dying men will graſp at all they ſee</l>
                  <l>While they can ſee, when Sence fails, farewell all,</l>
                  <l>The World's too heavy, then they let it fall.</l>
                  <l>Though we are born clutch-fiſted, when we die</l>
                  <l>We ſpread our Palms, and let them ſlip by;</l>
                  <l>And then when nothing elſe will with us ſtay,</l>
                  <l>We muſt our ſelves remain with Earth and Clay;</l>
                  <l>Since all I want here, God gives, and I have,</l>
                  <l>What can I more expect now but my Grave?</l>
                  <l>Here muſt we be, and where elſe ſhall we reſt?</l>
                  <l>Is not a mans own Houſe, to ſleep in, beſt?</l>
                  <l>If this be all our Houſe, they are to blame,</l>
                  <l>That brag of the great Houſes whence they came;</l>
                  <l>And evermore their Speech they interlace,</l>
                  <l>I and my Fathers Houſe, Alas! Alas!</l>
                  <l>What is my Fathers Houſe, and what am I<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>My Fathers Houſe is Earth, where I muſt lye,</l>
                  <l>And I a Worm, no man, that fit no room,</l>
                  <l>Till like a Worm I crawl into my Tomb</l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:105161:6"/>
                  <l>This is my Dwelling, this my trueſt home,</l>
                  <l>A Houſe of Clay beſt fits a Houſe of Lome;</l>
                  <l>Nay 'tis my Houſe, for I perceive I have</l>
                  <l>In all my Life, ne're dwelt out of a Grave;</l>
                  <l>The Womb was firſt my Grave, whence ſince I roſe</l>
                  <l>My Body Grave-like doth my Soul incloſe,</l>
                  <l>Dying each Night, lyes buryed in my Bed,</l>
                  <l>My Body like a Corps with Sheets o'reſpread,</l>
                  <l>O're which my ſpreading Teaſtures large extent,</l>
                  <l>Born up with Antiques, makes my Monument;</l>
                  <l>And o're my head perchance ſuch things may ſtand,</l>
                  <l>When I am quite run out in Duſt and Sand;</l>
                  <l>My cloſe low builded Chamber to my Eye,</l>
                  <l>Like to a Chappel ſhews, wherein I lye,</l>
                  <l>While at my Window pritty Birds do ring</l>
                  <l>My Knell, and with their Notes my Obits ſing:</l>
                  <l>Thus when the days vain toil my Soul hath wear'd</l>
                  <l>I in my Body, Bed, and Houſe, lie buryed.</l>
                  <l>Then have I little cauſe to fear my Tomb,</l>
                  <l>When this wherein I live is my Grave become;</l>
                  <l>Nay, we do not only our ſelves intomb,</l>
                  <l>But make for others, Graves in our own Womb,</l>
                  <l>Creatures of Sea and Land we in them bury,</l>
                  <l>And at their Funerals are blith and merry,</l>
                  <l>Who groan to ſerve us thus, and die unwilling,</l>
                  <l>How can we then live long, who live by killing?</l>
                  <l>Methinks we ſhould neither eat nor drink,</l>
                  <l>But ſtrait to dig our Graves we ſhould bethink;</l>
                  <l>For ſince by their dead Bodies we are fed,</l>
                  <l>I wonder all this while we are not dead:</l>
                  <l>It is an old ſaid Law, yet ſtill in requeſt,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>When Belly is full, then Bones would be at reſt.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Well, have we fed the Fleſh? and from Sins Cup,</l>
                  <l>Have drunk Iniquity like water up;</l>
                  <l>The Creatures we have eaten flead and ſhorn,</l>
                  <l>The Fruits from Earth to feed us, we have torn.</l>
                  <l>Are we not ſatisfied, Oh ſure 'tis beſt,</l>
                  <l>That after all we get our Bones to reſt,</l>
                  <l>And no where can the Fleſh true ſlumber have,</l>
                  <l>But in our trueſt home, our homely Grave;</l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:105161:6"/>
                  <l>There we ſleep ſound, there let the Tempeſts roar,</l>
                  <l>The Worlds proud Waves ſhall daſh on us no more</l>
                  <l>W're all deluded, vainly ſearching ways,</l>
                  <l>To make us happy by the length of days:</l>
                  <l>For cunningly to make's protract this breath,</l>
                  <l>The Gods conceal the happineſs of Death;</l>
                  <l>We are at home, and ſafe, whatever comes,</l>
                  <l>Let them fight on, we ſhall not hear their Drums;</l>
                  <l>Let thoſe be doted on, now love, or hate,</l>
                  <l>It ſhall not grieve us, though they prove ingrate;</l>
                  <l>Yea, let them praiſe, or rule, we lie aloof</l>
                  <l>Out of their reach, our ſleep is Cannon proof;</l>
                  <l>And we but ſleep, for as we cloſe our eyes,</l>
                  <l>Each night we go to Bed in hopes to riſe;</l>
                  <l>So do we die, for when the Trump doth blow,</l>
                  <l>We ſhall as eaſily awake we know,</l>
                  <l>And as we after ſleep, our Bodies find</l>
                  <l>More freſh in ſtrength, and chearfully inclin'd;</l>
                  <l>So after Death, our Fleſh here dead and dried,</l>
                  <l>Shall riſe Immortal, new and purified;</l>
                  <l>If this be true, why make we no more haſt,</l>
                  <l>'Tis time to ſleep, day fails, Night draws on faſt,</l>
                  <l>Let's get us home, for as the Evening Sun,</l>
                  <l>Looking us in the face when day is done</l>
                  <l>Makes us caſt longer Shadows, ſo when Death</l>
                  <l>Looks in our face through Age and claims our Breath,</l>
                  <l>We caſt his ſhadow long off from our ſight,</l>
                  <l>Yet may we know right well 'tis almoſt night,</l>
                  <l>And when we ſee night come in frowning Skies,</l>
                  <l>What man will not go home, if he be wiſe?</l>
                  <l>Here let him come, this Houſe is of ſuch faſhion,</l>
                  <l>The Tenant ne're ſhall pay for Reparation,</l>
                  <l>There ſhall the Due not wet him, Cold not harm him,</l>
                  <l>There ſhall no Summer weather over warm him.</l>
                  <l>From thence he'l find, when thither he is gone,</l>
                  <l>A private Walk to Heaven for 'mſelf alone:</l>
                  <l>Why do we not then go? Are Fleſh and Blood</l>
                  <l>The hinderers that clog us from our Good?</l>
                  <l>Oh! rie thy ſelf at home, and caſt off thoſe,</l>
                  <l>What wiſe man ever went to bed in's Cloaths?</l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:105161:7"/>
                  <l>Shall we that know how after this Life ends,</l>
                  <l>An Everlaſting one for us attends,</l>
                  <l>Grieve to lay down theſe rags for Earth to keep,</l>
                  <l>That we a while may take a nap of Sleep.</l>
                  <l>Then were we worſe than children: for but ſay,</l>
                  <l>That they to morrow ſhall have Holy-day,</l>
                  <l>They'l ſtreight to bed, and put off all Apparel:</l>
                  <l>Then ceaſe, my Fleſh, with Heavens Decree to quarrel,</l>
                  <l>And with theſe words reduce thy Thoughts that come,</l>
                  <l>He that dies firſt, ſhall only firſt go home;</l>
                  <l>But when thy Fleſh hither to thee prepares,</l>
                  <l>Say, as when thou goeſt to bed, thy Prayers;</l>
                  <l>Since he moſt oft forgets himſelf in Death,</l>
                  <l>That thinks not of his God that gives him breath;</l>
                  <l>Invoke his Mercy e're thy reſt thou take,</l>
                  <l>For as thou fall'ſt aſleep, ſo ſhalt thou wake;</l>
                  <l>This Houſe, of which before we have been telling,</l>
                  <l>Is but a ſleeping Chamber, not a Dwelling:</l>
                  <l>For when thou wak'ſt, this Houſe no more ſhall hold thee,</l>
                  <l>But that whereof the bleſſed Apoſtle told thee,</l>
                  <l>Saying, <hi>If this our earthly Houſe ſhall once decay,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>We have a Houſe not made by hands with Clay,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But in the Heavens.</hi> Eternal bleſt is he,</l>
                  <l>Whom thou, O Lord, admitteſt there to be,</l>
                  <l>He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>thy Courts ſhall dwell, thy Temples ſtore</l>
                  <l>Shall in thy Houſe fill him for evermore;</l>
                  <l>But ſtay, my Soul, thou canſt not yet come thither,</l>
                  <l>Thy Wings are clog'd, and thou more ſtrength muſt gather;</l>
                  <l>Mean time till from the Earth thou get'ſt free ſcope,</l>
                  <l>Even in thy Grave thy Fleſh ſhall reſt in Hope.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Meditations on Sleep.</head>
                  <l>THe Night is come like to the Day,</l>
                  <l>Depart not thou, great God away;</l>
                  <l>Let not my ſins, black as the Night,</l>
                  <l>Ecclipſe the luſtre of thy Light;</l>
                  <l>Keep ſtill in my Horizon, for to me</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Sun</hi> makes not the Day, but thee;</l>
                  <l>Thou whoſe Nature cannot ſleep,</l>
                  <l>On my Temples Centinel keep,</l>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:105161:7"/>
                  <l>Guard me againſt thoſe watchful Foes,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Eyes are open while mine cloſe,</l>
                  <l>Let no Dreams my Head infeſt,</l>
                  <l>But ſuch as <hi>Jacobs</hi> Temples bleſt;</l>
                  <l>Whil'ſt I do reſt, my Soul advance,</l>
                  <l>And make my reſt an holy Trance,</l>
                  <l>That I may, my reſt being wrought,</l>
                  <l>Be wak't into ſome holy thought,</l>
                  <l>And with an active vigour run</l>
                  <l>My Courſe, as doth the nimble <hi>Sun;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Sleep is a Death, Oh make me try,</l>
                  <l>By ſleeping, what it is to dye;</l>
                  <l>And as gently lay my head</l>
                  <l>On my Grave, as now my Bed;</l>
                  <l>How ere I reſt, great God, let me</l>
                  <l>Awake again at laſt with thee;</l>
                  <l>And thus aſſur'd, behold I lye</l>
                  <l>Securely whether to wake, or dye;</l>
                  <l>Theſe are my drowzy Days, in vain</l>
                  <l>I do now wake to ſleep again:</l>
                  <l>Oh come that hour, when I ſhall never</l>
                  <l>Sleep no more, but wake for ever.</l>
                  <l>Thus ſhall I take leave of the <hi>Sun,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Deſiring ſleep till th' Reſurrection.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Againſt Drowzineſs.</head>
                  <l>Permit not ſluggiſh ſleep</l>
                  <l>To cloſe your waking Eye,</l>
                  <l>Till you with Judgment deep</l>
                  <l>Your dayly Actions try;</l>
                  <l>He that his ſins as Darlings keeps,</l>
                  <l>When he to quiet goes,</l>
                  <l>More deſperate is, than he that ſleeps</l>
                  <l>Among his mortal Foes;</l>
                  <l>At Night lye down prepar'd to have</l>
                  <l>Thy ſleep thy Death, thy Bed thy Grave,</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:105161:8"/>
               <lg>
                  <head>On Patience.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Patience</hi> is the Poor mans Walk,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Patience</hi> is the Dumb mans Talk,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Patience</hi> is the Lame mans Thighs,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Patience</hi> is the Blind mans Eyes.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Patience</hi> is the Poor mans ditty.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Patience</hi> is the Exil'd mans City.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Patience</hi> the ſick mans Bed of Down.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Patience</hi> is the Wiſe man Crown.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Patience</hi> is the live mans Story.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Patience</hi> is the dead mans Glory.</l>
                  <l>When your Troubles do controul,</l>
                  <l>In Patience poſſeſs your Soul.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>FFormerly, when I have ſeriouſly thought and remembred my Vow in <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> it hath made me couragious to fight againſt the <hi>World,</hi> the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and the <hi>Devil,</hi> which hath made me often take up Reſolutions, that I would ſcorn to be a Coward: but as Fools make a mock at Sin, ſo have I deceived my ſelf by too eager pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Worldly Vanities, thinking to have found undermoon Comforts, till I found my ſelf beſet with Snares, and that there were bitter things written againſt me, which pierced me with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, and I was almoſt in deſpair, had I not been ſuſtained with theſe Comforts following, which hath ſince much refreſhed me, and vanquiſhed the Tempter, ſo that now I do rejoyce in God my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, and the Lord hath thus ſpoken. <hi>Oh my Beloved, why feareſt thou, and art ſo caſt down, and diſquieted within thy ſelf? Doſt thou well to be angry with my Chaſtiſements? And why art thou offended that I ſhould make thee like my ſelf? Cauſing thee to walk in the way of inward and outward Griefs, which I did tread before thee. Why refuſeſt thou to take up my Croſs and follow me, and to taſte of that Cup which I drank before, and for thee?</hi> (The <hi>Soul</hi>) Oh Lord, give me of thy Spirit, and all trouble with thee, or for thee, ſhall be ſweet unto me. What ever thou didſt, Oh Lord, it was for me; and if I were ſo diſpoſed, as I ſhould, then would I be content to bear all that thou my God ſhouldſt be pleaſed to lay upon me. But alas! it is my curſed Corruptions that makes me think thy Croſs my Burthen. Lord therefore uphold me by thy Grace, that I may count thy Yoak eaſie, and find joy in theſe Sufferings with thee.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:105161:8"/>
               <p>The Lord. <hi>I know the Cauſe of thy Grief and Terrour to be the Conſideration of thy Sins. But I pray thee, Why lookeſt thou ſo to thy Sins, that thou lookeſt not to my Mercies? Why wouldſt thou ſo extol thy evil Deeds, that thou ſhouldſt extenuate my rich Mercies, or any way compare the one with the other? Was it for thy good Deeds that I did firſt enter into Friendſhip with thee? And thinkeſt thou now that for thy evil Deeds I will utterly forſake thee? Seeing it is among my Praiſes, that the Work which I have begun, I will perfect it. I like it well indeed, to ſee thee grieved for the Sins thou haſt committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me: But I would alſo have thee comforted in the Mercies that I have ſhewed thee: Call to mind my Works of old, &amp; what I have done to thee ſince thou canſt remember. How cared I for thee in thy young and tender Years? Look back now and ſee. Did not the Angel of my Preſence lead thee when thou hadſt no wiſdom nor ſtrength to govern thee? Did not I then begin to acquaint thee with the Knowledge and Fear of my Name? Canſt thou deny now that my Mercy preſerved thee from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Sins whereunto thy Nature was prone, and ready to have declined? And when thou ſinnedſt, with what long patience have I waited thy turning, and how lovingly have I winked at thy Tranſgreſſions? And when I had given thee Grace to repent of thy Sins, and to ſeek for my Favour and Mercy for the Sins of thy youth, with a melting heart and a mourning eye. Canſt thou deny that I have filled thy Heart with my Joys, and made thy tongue to burſt out in ſinging and glorying Speeches? And why then wilt thou not truſt in my Mercies to the end?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>(The Soul)</hi> I were, O Lord, moſt unthankful if I ſhould not confeſs, that many a time in the multitude of my thoughts, thy <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> have comforted me. But alas! I have not anſwered thy Loving Kindneſs; for after many <hi>Mercies</hi> received, I have ſinned againſt thee contrary to my Light; and my ſins are now before me, witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that I am unworthy to taſte of the ſweetneſs of thy <hi>Mercies</hi> any more. (The Lord) <hi>Is my Mercy only for a Day, or a Year? Or is it for ever and ever towards thoſe that I have made mine in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus? Wilt thou reſtrain my Mercies, and limit them within thy narrow Bounds, as to think they cannot be extended over all thy Tranſgreſſions? Wilt thou meaſure my Mercies with ſo narrow a ſpan, as to think that I have no more to give than thou haſt to receive. Is it not among my Praiſes,</hi> That I am able to do exceeding abundantly, above all that my Children can ask, or think, of me. <hi>Knoweſt thou not, that as the Heavens are above the Earth, ſo are my Thoughts above thine? Haſt thou not conſidered that my Mercy is above all my Works? How much
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105161:9"/>more then is it above thee, who art nothing in compariſon of my migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Works? And if it be above thee, how much more above all thou canſt do. Why then wilt thou match thy Sins with my Mercies? If I require ſuch Mercy in my Children, that I will have them to forgive one another, not only ſeven times, but ſeventy times ſeven times. What pitty, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, and readineſs to forgive is in my ſelf. Therefore my Beloved, deſpair not for the multitude of thy Sins; but be comforted with my Promiſes of Mercy. I have made them without Exceptions of Sins: For albeit they were Sins of Scarlet, they ſhall be made white as Wool. I have made them without exception of Perſons. For whoſoever ſhall depart from his Wickedneſs and turn to me, I will receive him. Let this threefold <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſality of my Promiſes ſuſtain thee, that thy Infidelity contract not my Mercy into narrower bounds than I have extended them. (The Soul)</hi> Be merciful, O Lord to my Infidelity. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in part, Lord, help my Unbelief. Eſtabliſh and confirm my unſtable heart with thy good Spirit. My Conſcience doth in ſuch ſort condemn me, that I ſtand in fear of thy Juſtice; for thou art greater than my Conſcience, and wilt much more condemn me, if thou doſt enter into Judgment with me. (The Lord) <hi>Oh my Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, conſider that the Cauſe of thy preſent <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nquietneſs is, becauſe with the one Eye thou lookeſt to thy Sins, and my Fathers Juſtice, and with thy other Eye lookeſt not to me, in whom his Juſtice is ſatisfied, and thy Sins puniſhed already. Tell me, I pray thee, Thinkeſt thou in thy ſelf, to get ſuch a Holineſs of thy Diſpoſition, that which ſhall exempt thee from the Fear of his Juſtice? Or art thou content to ſeek it in me? If in thy ſelf thou ſeekeſt it, remember what thou art doing. Wilt thou have the Lord bound and oblieged to thee? Wilt thou be thy own Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour? Or ſhall it be ſaid,</hi> His Mercy Saved thee not. <hi>If no miſery were in thee, whereupon ſhould his Mercy be manifeſted? And if thy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition in the Earth be ſuch as it ſhould be, then what remains, but that the Praiſe of his Mercy ſhould fall to the ground. Turn thee therefore to me, and ſeek thy Life in me. If thou wilt know what is thine, thou art a Sinner. Let my Praiſe be reſerved to my ſelf. I am thy Saviour. Eſteemeſt thou that my words are ineffectual, or that there is no force in my Suffering. Counteſt thou thy Sins ſo deadly, that my Merit &amp; Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue cannot cure them: Will a Phyſitian pour out a rare Ointment either where no need it, or where it cannot profit: and thinkeſt thou that my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would have my Blood to be ſhed in vain. If his Juſtice terrifies thee, remember his Juſtice was ſatisfied in me, and that he pronounceth this Sentence Himſelf;</hi> This is my Beloved Son in whom I am well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. <hi>I came into the W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ld, not to call the Righteous, but Sinners to Repentance. Tarry not from me becauſe thou art a Sinner, but for that Cauſe come unto me, &amp; I will refreſh thee</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:105161:9"/>
               <p>(The Soul) <hi>Oh Lord, I know there is a cleanſing and reco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ding Vertue in thy Blood. That Life is in thy Death. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ll I fear my Sins deſerve that thou ſhouldſt never apply thy Vertue, nor thy Merits to me: for alas, I find that the Old man is lively and ſtrong in me; and that the motions of Sin have power in me to bring forth Fruits un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Death. (The Lord)</hi> Be not I pray thee injurious to thy ſelf in the work of my Grace in thee; Complain not of thy Corruptions. But that thou mayſt give unto me my own praiſe. Canſt thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny but thou haſt felt my Power working in thy Soul? Have I no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſprinkled thy Conſcience many times with the purifying and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifying Blood of Chriſt, from which hath flowed to thee ſuch a witneſſing of good things, ſuch a ſence of Mercies, as for the time hath filled thy heart with Joys, &amp; thy mouth with Songs of Praiſe? Have I not ſtirred thee up ſometimes with great fervency to call up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Name of the Lord? Have I not made thee to give Chriſts Name a publick Teſtimony with thine own diſadvantage? And how often hath thy heart been effectually moved at the hearing of my Word, in ſuch ſort, that it wrought in thee a holy Remorſe, and an inward Contrition for Sin, which hath broken out into tears? Have I not made thee to wreſtle againſt thine inordinate Luſts? Have I not given thee Strength many a time to ſtand againſt <hi>Satans</hi> Temptations? Whereas if I had left thee to thy ſelf, how often hadſt thou been made a Prey to thine Enemy? Remembreſt thou not that the Tempter hath often aſſaulted thee? But I have with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn the occaſion of Sin: and when the occaſion hath ſerved, did I not reſtrain and hold back the Tempter? Yea, when both the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion and Tempter were preſent, have I not filled thy heart with the Fear and Love of my Name, and ſo kept thee from ſinning againſt me? And whereas many times of thy weakneſs thou haſt offended, Did not I with a melting heart and mourning eye raiſe thee again, and renew my former familiarity with thee? So that thou canſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſay, from the firſt hour that I begun to renew thee, that I have ſuffered thee to lye in thy Sin, as I have done others that are S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to my Grace; and many notable Effects of my working in thee, thou canſt not deny. Are not theſe the undoubted Tokens of my Grace in thee? Will Nature do ſuch things? Mayſt thou not feel by theſe, that I have begun to apply to thee Chriſts Merits for the Remiſſion of thy Sins, and Chriſts Vertue for quickening thee to a new Life? Therefore think of thy ſelf as barely as thou wilt; but let the Work of my Grace be eſteemed by thee accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:105161:10"/>to the excellency of it. Be humble and caſt down when thou lookeſt on thine own corruption. I find no fault with thee, but I rejoyce and am glad of the new Workmanſhip which I have begun in thee. Indeed if there were nothing in thee but that which thou haſt by nature, thy ſtate were very miſerable: but ſeeing thou find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt a new Workmanſhip in thee, be comforted. Art thou in Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that there is no Light in thee? Or doth Sin poſſeſs thee, that beſides it, alſo there is not a Will in thee to do Good, and a Love to Righteouſneſs. If thou ſaiſt that thou haſt no Sin in thee, thou art a <hi>Lyer.</hi> And if thou ſaiſt thou haſt no other thing in thee but Sin, thou art alſo a <hi>Lyer.</hi> And thinkeſt thou that ſeeing I have begun to tranſlate thee into my Light, and to make thee a new Creature, thinkeſt thou that I will leave thee till I have done, till I have done my Work in thee. Therefore my Beloved give not ſuch ear to <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi> and thy own Corruptions, as to take this Teſtimony againſt me, or make thee think that my Pledges which I have given thee, are not worthy of Credit, that by <hi>them</hi> thou ſhouldſt be aſſured of my <hi>Mercy.</hi> (The Soul) <hi>I cannot deny, O Lord, but that many times I have felt the ſweetneſs of thy heavenly Conſolations, which have greatly rejoyced my Soul. But alas! my grief is ſo much the more, that by my own Defaults I ſhould now be deprived of them: for I have grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved thy Holy Spirit; yea, I have done what I could to quench him, and therefore it is, that the Comforter who was wont to refreſh my Soul, is away, nor can I feel his Preſence with me as before. (The Lord)</hi> Becauſe I am not changed, therefore it is that ye, O Sons of <hi>Jacob,</hi> are not conſumed: many are the Changes indeed whereunto you are ſubject, but I remain the ſame, and there is no ſhadow of alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration with me. Be not therefore afraid, O my Beloved, neither eſteem thy ſelf to be rejected of me; albeit that ſometimes I hide my face from thee. All my ways are Mercy and Truth to mine. It is for thee that ſometimes I go from thee, and it is for thee that again I do return unto thee: for if I come, it is for thy Conſolation, that continual heavineſs ſhould not oppreſs thee by thy manifold Temptations. How often haſt thou found this when thou wert ſick of Love: I have ſtrengthened thee with Flagons of my own, and comforted thee wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> my Apples: my Fruit hath been ſweet in thy mouth, and I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> put my Left-hand under thy Head, and with my Right-hand I have imbraced thee. But leaſt the greatneſs of my Conſolations ſhould exalt thee to diſdain thy Brother, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend me, by imputing that to thy own diſpoſition, which thou haſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:105161:10"/>of my Diſpenſation, I have again withdrawn theſe glorious feelings from thee; give me the Praiſe, that I know beſt what is expedient for thee. Had my Servant St. <hi>Paul</hi> need to be humbled with the Buffets of <hi>Satan,</hi> leaſt he ſhould be exalted above meaſure by the greatneſs of his Revelations? And haſt not thou need, that by thy inward Exerciſes I ſhould hold thee humble? If my Comforts were always preſent with thee, thou wouldſt think thy Heaven, thy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent City, were here on Earth, and ſo ceaſe to enquire for a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to come; thou wouldſt take the place of thy Baniſhment for thy Home, and thy Earneſt for thy Principal Sum which I have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed thee. Conſider this wiſely with thy ſelf, and albeit I laugh not alike on thee at all times, and fill thee not always with Joys, yet I always love thee; for whom I love, it is to the end; If I cloſe the Door of my Chamber upon thee, it is not to hold thee out, but to leave thee to knock: If I cover my ſelf with my Veiles, that thou canſt not ſee a glance of my Countenance, it is only to ſtir thee up to ſeek me: and if ſometimes I ſeem to go from thee, it is to provoke thee to follow me, that thou mayſt make haſt from Earth to Heaven, where thou ſhalt injoy me without Intermiſſion. Was <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſo wiſe, as to conceal his tender Affections from his Brethren, till he had brought them to an humble acknowledgment of their Sin: and was he again ſo loving, that when he ſaw them humbled, his Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were inflamed, and compelled him to reveal himſelf unto them. And thinkeſt thou that I am leſs wiſe and loving in dealing with mine. I gave at firſt, ſharp Anſwers to the Petitions of that Woman of <hi>Canaan;</hi> and ſo will I ſometimes ſeem to deal roughly with thoſe whom I love, and to be angry even with their Prayers, but in the end I will make my Love manifeſt to them, and with my endleſs Mercies embrace them. (The <hi>Soul</hi>) <hi>Suffer me once again, Lord to ſpeak, that thou mayſt anſwer me, and I ſhall complain no more. If we ſaw that ſuch were our Diſpoſitions, as thy moſt Holy Word doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire in us, then ſhould thy Comforts rejoyce us. But alas! How far am I from that which I ſhould be; my ſtrength is infeebled, therefore do my inordinate Affections oftentimes overcharge me. If I turn me to pray, I cannot for the hardneſs of my heart: the contrite Spirit, the melting heart, and mourning Eye are gone from me: If I ſeek Comfort in thy Word, I find it not; I am troubled alſo with doubtings, Armies of Fears and Terrours are againſt me, and all through the weakneſs of my Faith, and partly for want of that Light which ſhould inform me, my Infidelity abateth me, to think that thy Viſitations came from thine an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:105161:11"/>and cauſeth me to anſwer the Errours of my Conſcience as if they were juſt Accuſations, and partly for want of that apprehending and applying Vertue that is in Faith: I am ſpoiled of my Comfort that thy Word hath offered unto me. Therefore, O Lord, have pitty on the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate State of my poor Soul. (The Lord)</hi> Let not, my Beloved, the conſideration of thy Wants, Defects, and Imperfections diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage thee; remember that the meaſure of my Grace which I have given to my <hi>Saints</hi> upon Earth, I have called it an <hi>Earneſt-Penny,</hi> and <hi>Firſt Fruits of the Spirit,</hi> to tell them, that what ever Grace they have gotten, it is nothing in compariſon of that which they will get: ſeek not that therefore in Earth which I have reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved no ways to give it thee, till thou doſt come to Heaven. Thy Bleſſedneſs in this Life ſtands not in a ſaciety and full injoying of that which thou wouldſt have in a hungring and thirſting for it. If I had pronounced them happy and bleſſed, that are now ſatisfied with righteouſneſs, then thy wants might have moſt juſtly diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged thee; but I called them bleſſed that hunger. If thou therefore doſt follow after <hi>Sanctification,</hi> and art weary of the ſervitude of thy ſins; if thou ſhouldſt ſeek comfort in my Word, and couldſt ſind none of theſe at the firſt as thou wouldſt; yet remember that I have promiſed to fulfil the Deſires of thoſe that fear me: if it doth grieve thee that thou canſt not pray at all times alike, remember that my Children are often times ill Judges of themſelves, and that their Eſtate is not always to be meaſured by their feeling; for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Prayers may be made by them to me by my Spirit, with ſighs and ſobs that they themſelves are not able to expreſs, yet are known to me, and are like loud crying Voices, which I cannot but anſwer. (The <hi>Soul) Oh my Soul, content thee with the Lords Diſpenſations, and doubt not but all thy Wants and Deſires that are holy ſhall once be ſatisfied, remember how careful thy Saviour was of the People that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed him;</hi> I have compaſſion <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> on theſe People, becauſe they have nothing to eat, they have continued with me already three days, I will not let them depart faſting, leaſt they faint by the way. <hi>O moſt ſweet and comfortable Speeches, they ſeek not from him, and he is careful to give them. If he was ſo careful to ſatisfie their bodily Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities, will be neglect the Spiritual Neceſſities of his own choſen Ones: they followed him three days, and he counted it a long time; they are to go from Him, and he feareth leſt they ſhould faint. Oh my diſtruſtful Soul, wilt thou once learn to truſt in the Mercies of thy God aſſuredly? Will not he ſatiate thee who ſeeks Him? Will not he anſwer thee who
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:105161:11"/>cryes unto Him? Will he not care for thee who hast waited upon Him, not only three days, but many Years? And will he let thee faint in fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of Him, who would not let them faint in going from Him. O ſweet Savour! happy are thoſe that truſt in thee: Lord, therefore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ereaſe my Faith in thee, that nothing may ever be able to ſunder me from thee. (The Lord)</hi> As for the weakneſs of thy Faith, which I ſee is the ground of all thy trouble, it proceedeth either from the want of knowledge, or elſe from the want of Application. It is indeed a ſpecial benefit to have the Mind enlightned with true Light: ſeek therefore my Light to ſhine into thee, by continual Prayer, and ſcarching the Scriptures, that thou be not troubled with the Errour of Conſcience, as if it were a juſt Accuſation: I have ſet Conſcience indeed to be a Warner unto thee, but then ſhalt thou take heed to her Warnings, when they are warranted by my Word: if the errour of Conſcience terrifie thee in any thing, and make thee think that thy Croſſes and Viſitations do come from mine anger, go and inform Conſcience better by my Word: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, <hi>Whom I chaſtiſe, I love.</hi> And when I chaſtiſe thee, I am not ſeeking ſatisfaction to my Juſtice, what marvel, ſuch Thoughts diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet many. Conſider, I pray thee, that notable Promiſe of mine made to my Servant <hi>David,</hi> and in him, to all the reſt of my <hi>Saints; If they break my Statutes, I will viſit their Tranſgreſſions with Rods, yet my Loving Kindneſs will I not take from them, neither alter my Covenant for ever.</hi> (The <hi>Soul) Oh Word full of Comfort, my Soul, forget it never; that when his Rods are laid upon thee, yet his Loving Kindneſs is not taken from thee, and though thy Tranſgreſſions be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, yet will he not alter his Covenant with thee: remember it, I ſay, that it thy trouble thou give no more place to the Miſconceptions of Gods Workings with thee, as Godly</hi> Job <hi>thought in his trouble, that the Lord was purſuing him for his Sins, and made him poſſeſs the Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of his Youth; which as yet appears by the Courſe of that Hiſtory, was not the Lords Intention. So have I thought many times, that the heavy Hand of the Lord laid on me, had proceeded from his Wrath, as if he had ſhut up his Mercy in diſpleaſure for ever: but Lord, let thy Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Light abide with me, that I ſin no more with ſuch diſtruſtful Motions against thee: and now Lord, ſpeak on further to thy Servant, for thy Comforts have refreſhed me, and rejoyeed my Soul. (The Lord)</hi> As for the weakneſs of thy Faith, which I ſee is the ground of all thy trouble, it proceedeth either from the want of Knowledge, or elſe from the want of Application. It is indeed a ſpecial benefit
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:105161:12"/>to have the Mind enlightned with true Light; ſeek therefore my Light to ſhine into thee by continual Prayer, and ſearching of the Scriptures, that thou be not troubled with the errour of Conſcience, as if it were a juſt Accuſation. Now concerning the weakneſs of thy Faith in the Apprehenſion and Application of my Promiſes: remember that I am He, that <hi>Will not break the bruiſed Reed, nor quench the ſmoaking Flax.</hi> What ſmaller thing is there than a grain of <hi>Muſtard-ſeed?</hi> Albeit if the meaſure of thy Faith were no more, yet have I not excluded it from the participation of my Promiſes. A loving Father will delight to be holden by the hand of his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; and knoweſt thou not, that as a Father ſpareth his Son, ſo will the Lord ſpare them that fear Him. Haſt thou not read, that although the Faith of my Servant <hi>Jacob</hi> was very weak, as thou mayſt perceive by the great fear he conceived of his Brother <hi>Eſau;</hi> yet his weak Faith was able to hold me till I bleſſed him. Be not therefore diſcouraged; for although thou canſt not lay hold of me by the hand of ſtrong Faith, if thou canſt but touch the Hem of my Garment with thy finger, thou ſhalt draw vertue out of me. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider alſo with thy ſelf, that the Faith of my Children is never greater, than when their feeling is weakeſt, and leaſt perceived. It is eaſie for every one to believe in the midſt of great Feelings, and unſpeakable Joys: but when a man can feel no ſenſible Comfort in me, and yet believe and truſt in me, and ſtill believe and wait on me for Comfort, certainly the Faith of that man is great: and ſuch was the Faith of my Servant, who in his greateſt troubles gave me this anſwer, <hi>Albeit thou ſhouldſt ſlay me, O Lord, yet both againſt Sence and Feeling will I trust in thee.</hi> And did not alſo that Woman of <hi>Canaan,</hi> with an invincible Faith cleave to my Mercy, even then when ſhe had no feeling of Mercy; and I gave her no favourable anſwer? For which, in the end, I called her Faith <hi>a great Faith.</hi> (The <hi>Soul) O my Saviour, thou art the Strength whereby I stand in Temptations. Curſed be he that would make my Soul to conceive wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully of thee. Be merciful, O Lord unto me, and never let the malice of my Enemies prevail over me. Sweet Jeſus, keep the Heart that through thy own Grace would fain keep thee. And now, my Soul, remember, that this is but the time of Fighting; the time of Triumphing will come. Why then ſhall the continuance of theſe restleſs Aſſaults diſquiet thee? If thou hadst never been Victorious but once in all thy Life time, yet what Mercy had it been, that the Lord in the midst of the Battle ſhould make thee to Triumph. But thou canst not deny but that many joyful Victories
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:105161:12"/>now, and before hath the Lord given thee? Therefore, my Soul, rejoice and return to thy former reſt, for the Mighty God hath been beneficial unto thee: and account every one of theſe Temporal Victories to be a Pledge to thee of the full and final Victory that once thou ſhalt enjoy over all thine Enemies, when the God of Peace ſhall tread Satan under thy Feet. O Lord, if ſuch Comforts be in the Croſs, what is in the Crown? And if thou giveſt us ſuch Joy when thou takeſt us into thy Hand to correct us with thy Rod, Lord, what wilt thou make us to find when thou ſhalt imbrace us in thy Arms, and kiſs us with the Kiſſes of thy Mouth? Oh that theſe Feelings might ever abide with me. What trouble would not be eaſie, when thy Comforts are preſent? Surely, O Lord, all trouble vaniſheth ſo ſoon as thou doſt begin to glace upon my Soul. Therefore, O my Love, my Light, my Life, my Joy, my Crown, my Glory, my Strength, my Help in time of need, ſtand thou on my ſide, and I will not fear what mine Enemies can do unto me. O happy time, that I ever knew thee: bleſſed be the Name of the Lord for evermore: O Enemy Satan, albeit thy Enmity be trouble ſome unto me, yet I thank my God through Jeſus Chriſt, that thou art againſt me, and that he hath put me in the Warfare to fight againſt thee; when I conſider that in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice the Lord proclaimed irreconciliable Enmity between thee and my Bleſſed Saviour, the Seed of the Woman, Chriſt Jeſus, I account my Hope happy, that thou art against me, and that Grace is given unto me to fight againſt thee; for thereby I know that I am none of thine: but I do ſtand on that Side whereof Chriſt is the Captain, all his Saints are Souldiers, and the Victory is most certain. O deceitful Serpent, if I have found ſuch Errour ariſing of thoſe Sins which fooliſhly I did by thy Inticements, what ſhould I have found if I had followed thee in all the rest? From which the Lords preventing Mercy did keep me. I have learned by Experience, that thou art a faithleſs falſe Traytor, thou doſt tempt a man to Sin, and then for the ſame Sin that he did by thy Insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, thou art the first that doth accuſe him. The Lord confirm this good Purpoſe of my Heart, that I never hearken any more to thy lying Words, and ſuffer not my Soul to be circumvented by thy lying Snares, which are deceitful. And as for the Work of my Salvation, ſeeing it is a Work that my God will work in deſpite of thee, wherefore ſhall I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard thy Testimony. Thou didst put in question, Whether my Saviour were the Son of God? And what marvel if thou doſt ſay to his Children, that they are none of his. Is there any Truth ſo undoubted, but thou darest deny it at any time? Why ſhall I therefore at any time enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a diſputing with thee any more? My Salvation ſtandeth not in thy
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:105161:13"/>queſtioning, nor in my anſwering, but in the Lords unchangeable De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of Election: if thou ſhoulſt ſpeak for me, yet ſhould I not be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; neither if thou ſpeakest againſt me, am I the worſe. When thou didſt confeſs that Jeſus was the Son of God, he rebuked thee, and thought it not Honour to Him for to have thy Teſtimony. When thou didſt cry out, that</hi> Paul <hi>and</hi> Silas <hi>were the Servants of the Moſt High God, albeit thou ſpakeſt the Truth, yet did they not accept of thy Teſtimony. So although thou wouldſt ſay to me, that I am not the Elect Child of God, ſhall I think my ſelf ever the more unſure for that: and if on the contrary, thou ſhouldſt deny it, I am therefore the more ſure of my Salvation. Speak what thou wilt, thou art always a Lyar, like thy ſelf, as thou haſt been from the Beginning. Curſed of the Lord art thou in all thy ways, and with all thy Confederates. Curſed are all they that are in Friendſhip with thee. And Bleſſed for ever be the Lord, who hath delivered me from all thy Deceit and Tyranny. Bleſſed be thou, O Lord, that it hath pleaſed thee to viſit the baſe Eſtate of thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, to ſucoour me in my diſtreſs, and to comfort me with thy Mercies, Lord, evermore feed me with this Manna, and refreſh me with the Springs of the Water of Life: ſhew at all times ſome of thy Mercy to me, that my Enemy Satan, who laboureth to diſquiet me, may be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, becauſe thou art with me always to ſuccour me. If ye will mark and conſider, you ſhall find that the Children of God, in all their Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, are not ſo much Doers with their Will, as Sufferers againſt their Will: this Cogitation coming in my Mind, ſuddenly Comfort did ſpring in the midſt of my Trouble; God giving me Grace to underſtand that theſe Motions wherewith I am troubled, were not ſo many Actions done by me; for in truth, I do neither like, nor allow of them, but as Spiritual Oppreſſions of my Enemy, who ſtill warreth againſt me ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times with Armies of Fears, ſometimes with Armies of Doubtings, and with Armies of unclean and wandring Motions, and ſometimes with Bands and Troops of Worldly Cares, making Invaſion upon my Soul, and labouring to quench the ſparks of Spiritual Life, which the Lord had begun in me; therefore anſwer for me, O Lord, for I ſuffer Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, my Enemy would oppreſs me, but Lord, my hope is ever in thee, ſuccour me with thy ſtrength, and I ſhall live; and Lord, impute not to me any of thoſe ſinful Motions which mine Enemy raiſeth againſt me, and in me to deſtry my Soul. Conſider this wiſely, O my Soul, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member it; God that hath entred thee into this Warfare, and is a Spectator and Helper, will never reckon up to thee Satans Deeds for thine, and learn thou wiſely how to diſtinguiſh them, and faint not for
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:105161:13"/>them, but comfort thy ſelf as long as thou art able to ſtand to thy Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation, that thou doſt ſuffer Violence in them, and canſt ſay with the Apostle,</hi> This is not I, but Sin that dwelleth in me. <hi>O Lord, deliver me from the rage of this Tyranny; many a time have I looked to have been ſwallowed up of him, but thou hast ſustained me. Bleſſed be my God for ever, and the Lord be my strength to the end. O Lord, how can it be poſſible that my Soul can live here in this abſenſe from thee, or walk in the midſt of theſe continual Snares, or stand againſt theſe raging Temptations, except it pleaſe thee now and then to ſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thy Face unto me.</hi> Joſeph<hi>'s State in Priſon was not ſo heavy as mine, his Temptations in</hi> Potiphar's <hi>Houſe were not ſo continual as mine are And</hi> Daniel<hi>'s Fear in the midst of the Lions, was no greater than mine, who every day taſted of a thouſand Deaths.</hi> Jeremiah <hi>in a dark Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon, was not vexed with ſuch Horrors as dayly gather themſelves to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether about, and againſt me; the only comfort of my Soul is in the multitude of thy Mercies; thou wert with</hi> Joſeph, <hi>and therefore the Priſon was the more pleaſant to him than</hi> Potiphar<hi>'s Palace. Thou wert with</hi> Daniel, <hi>and therefore the raging Lions were peaceable to him. O Lord, be with me, and increaſe thy ſtrength in my Soul, and it ſhall live, though the time be not yet come that I ſhall appear in thy Preſence, and ſee thee, yet Lord, let me have in this Land of my Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage thoſe glances of thy ſweet and loving Countenance, that may ſustain me; for thou, Lord, art able to let me ſee as much joy in thy ſweet Face, in one hour, as may ſustain me for ever: and without this ſight, how can my Faith but fail, my Hope but hover, and my Life but languiſh? Therefore, O Lord, hide not thy Face from my Soul for ever: but as thou doſt acquaint my Soul with Troubles, ſo let me ſee at all times, that as my Sufferings do abound in me, ſo my Conſolations may abound through Jeſus Chriſt. I know thou always beholdeſt me in Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, but Lord, let me ſee that thou look'ſt upon me, that I may feel thy Mercies ſweet unto my Soul; and let me find every day by good Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that Jeſus Chriſt is formed in me, and inable me to live a holy Life here, ſo that I may live with thee a happy Life hereafter in thy Heavenly Kingdom for ever.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>IF thou art Learned, be alſo pious, for Learning ſanctified, is an Ornament to Grace: but Learning corrupted is an Advocate for the Devil. Call in mind, and oftentimes examine thy ſelf; ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting thy ſelf by thy Thoughts, Words, and Deeds, eſpecially
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:105161:14"/>after much Buſineſs, Diſcourſes, Paſtimes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Silence is commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable in things that appertain not to thee, to the end thou mayſt the better call to mind the Sufferings of a Crucifi'd Saviour. If God hath bleſſed thee with an Eſtate, relieve thy Brother, and ſo live as having little, yet poſſeſſing all things: for remember that Meat, Drink, and Cloaths are the Riches of a Chriſtian; and ſince Chriſt gave Himſelf for thee, well mayſt thou give ſome Fruits of thy Labour to thoſe that are his; let Death be oft-times the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of thy Meditations, yield thy ſelf wholly to God, if thou art poor, and haſt nothing to requite him with, but thy Prayers and thy ſelf; yet if thou giveſt thy ſelf to his diſpoſal, thou then giveſt all thou haſt; the Apoſtles left their Ships and their Nets; the poor <hi>Widdow</hi> gave only her two Mites to the <hi>Poor-mans-Box,</hi> and ſhe was preferred before a wealthy <hi>Craeſus.</hi> He eaſily diſpoſeth all things of this World, that doth but remember that he muſt dye, In open Aſſemblies uſe not always Spiritual Things, leaſt thou ſhalt be thought ſingular, except thou mayſt edifie others, and by thy Example, ſtir them up to the like: on all Occaſions prefer the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God and his Service above all things; be a Comfort to the afflicted, reconcile Differences, viſit the Sick and Impriſoned, and forget not to relieve the Poor and Needy; above all things have fervent Love, for Love ſhall cover a multitude of ſins: faſt one day in a Month, or oftner, if the ſtrength of thy Body will bear it, and remember to diſtribute thine Alms; for faſting and Alms are the Wings of Prayer; if Perturbations or Diſcontents ariſe in thy Mind, apply thy ſelf to Prayer, go not to thy Reſt in Wrath, leaſt thou giveſt the Common Enemy to Mankind an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to ſurprize thee; beware of inordinate Cares, leaſt you diſhonour or deny God; for ſuch Cares are needleſs, bruitiſh, boot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and heatheniſh. What need we care, when our Heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther knoweth that we have need of theſe things, and ſaith, <hi>Be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for nothing, but let us caſt our Cares upon him, for he careth for us: conſider the Fowls of the Air, and Ravens that he feeds, they toil not. Which of you by taking care, can add one Cubit to his Stature, or Penny to his Eſtate; for after theſe things the</hi> Gentiles <hi>ſeek: repent dayly, let not the Devil have the Flower of thy Age, and God the Bran. The Spirit of Prayer is far more precious than Treaſures of Gold and Silver. Deſpiſe not the Miniſters of Christ, for Christ is the Word, and they are his Ambaſſadors of it.</hi> God requireth we ſhould mortifie our Luſts; for Prayer without that is the Service
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:105161:14"/>of a Hypocrite: Sin bringeth ſhame and ſorrow, but Pity hath the portion of everlaſting Joys. Let us cloath our ſelves with everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Righteouſneſs, it is the ſafeſt Armour againſt the Darts of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan. The two Roads that lead to Heaven, are <hi>Innocence</hi> and <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; Sin</hi> is the Chriſtians greateſt <hi>Sore,</hi> and <hi>Repentance</hi> the ſureſt <hi>Salve:</hi> Who then would want the rare Jewel of <hi>Repentance,</hi> ſince if ye ſeek; ye ſhall find? Thy <hi>Soul</hi> is Spiritual, thy <hi>Body</hi> is Fleſh; make not then Fleſh of thy Spirit; for an habitual Familiarity with corrupt Luſts, perverts it into the baſeſt Fleſh: God hath made Man a lovely Creature, do not thou make thy ſelf a Monſter: he dignifies thee at firſt, to glorifie thee at laſt. Then let not Carnali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty deprive thee of thy Bleſſings; with thy Sins God will not own thee: if thou luſt, thou haſt loſt the ſenſe of Honour and Glory: ſtudy to recover it by Grace; thy Soul is Immortal, and cannot dye, thy Body is Mortal, and muſt dye: let not thy Body then be preferred before thy Soul, which hath but a <hi>Leaſe</hi> for Life; then let not a moment be preferred before Eternity; ſtudy not to ſatisfie thy Body and neglect the Salvation of thy moſt precious Soul. It is madneſs to ſeek the welfare of the Body, and thereby Eternally to ruine both Body and Soul: for ſo the Immortal is made moſt dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably Mortal, and dies to Bliſs, and the Mortal miſerably Immortal, and ever living to Wo: remember thy Soul is the Noble Part of humane Nature; wherefore to ſet thy Affections on Earth is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely below thee. Such is thy Nobility, thy Arms are thy Mind and thy Will, which were created to embrace Mercy, Truth, Juſtice, Charity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> With all the Vertues of a Heavenly Life: thy Body is Servant to thy Soul, let it tread upon the Earth, for that is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe its Subject; let not then the Soul, which is the Sovereign of the Body, ſet its Heart upon that Earth on which its Subject ſets its Foot. In thy Soul is the Image of God, let it not be ſtained then with the ſimilitude of a Beaſt; let Reaſon, not Sence divert thee, a rational Will, not the Appetite of a Bruit: he that lives a negligent and careleſs Life, does what he can to out do the Devil in his own undoing; for God hath given him Reaſon, and his depraved Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture acts againſt it. If thou wouldſt be in Eternal Bliſs, act like Man, but appear like God, for Heaven hath no room for Beaſts of the Earth; a wicked Spirit hath deformed thee, let a Holy Spirit transform thee; every Child of God ſhould maintain his Fathers Likeneſs, that he may enjoy his Inheritance. Thy Soul is the Spouſe of God, the great Creator is its Husband; no Creature is worthy to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:105161:15"/>be thy Match or Mate; then conſult thy Honour; if thou loveſt the World, and imbraceſt the Earth; canſt thou hate Adultery with men, and be an Adultreſs to God; let not a Strumpet ſtand in thy ſight; but eſpecially ſuffer not thy Heart to run after Vanity a whoring: if thou falleſt into evil Company, that ſhall court thee, let not the Devil woo thee. O my Soul, thou Beloved above all Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that haſt God for thy Husband, Heaven for thy Dowry, and Earth for thy Service; ſuffer not Hell to be thy <hi>Pander</hi> to dote up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the World, let thy Heart be a Habitation for God and Heaven: thy Soul is the Lord of thy Body, take then thy Bodies Homage, not thy own ruine; let thy Soul act the Will of God, &amp; command the will of thy Body to act thine: let not thy Body be thy God, leſt thou be a Devil to thy ſelf; thy Soul is an Angels Peer, let it not be a Companion for Satan; let not thy Lordſhip be ſold for Slavery and Miſery; if thou maintainſt not thy Right, Hell muſt be thy Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, Torments thy Terrour, and wicked Spirits thy Company. Thy Soul under God is the ſupream Sovereign of thy Body; be not then a <hi>Subject</hi> to thy <hi>Subject;</hi> let not the Law of the Members be the Law of the Mind, for the <hi>Senſes</hi> are Handmaids to the Soul, and ſhe is the Princeſs of Heaven, thy Soul is a free-born Child of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, Heir of Immencity, the Daughter of Almighty God, who is beyond all the Bounds of Time and Being: to whom then oughtſt thou to pay thy Duty, but to him alone: thy Body is but a Priſon to the Soul, thou art incloſed in the Wall of Mud, and Gates of Senſe: Can there be more pleaſure in a Priſon than in a Pallace? Shall a bodily reſtraint be preferred before the Spirits Liberty? Canſt thou count thy Bondage to be thy Bliſs? Are Chains of Iron to be eſteemed before the Treaſures of Gold? Are Fetters better than Freedom? Earth is but a Jayl to Heaven; then be not ſo raſh as to prize thy Jayl before thy Liberty and Delivery, leaſt thou art caſt into the Jayl from whence there is no Redemption. It is moſt juſt, that the Soul which prizeth the Devils Chain before Gods Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, ſhould have the Devils Priſon inſtead of Gods Pallace, and be for ever his <hi>Slave</hi> in Hell, that would not be Gods <hi>Servant</hi> for a Time on Earth. Then O thou Beloved Dove of God, fly to thy Coeleſtial Home: belime not thy <hi>Spiritual Wings</hi> with ſlime and mudd; in Heaven is thy Treaſure, and where canſt thou ſind more Tre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſures to invite thee? Be not like the <hi>Crow,</hi> to feed upon <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>on;</hi> or like the <hi>Blind Beetle,</hi> to place thy Bleſſedneſs in Boggs, Make not ſale of thy ſelf, to buy a Jayl, when thou parteſt with a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:105161:15"/>Pallace for the purchaſe, and becomeſt a Familiar to Bolts and Shacles: thy <hi>Soul</hi> is Gods Jewel, and thy <hi>Body</hi> is the Casket; then keep thy <hi>Body</hi> clean, that thy <hi>Soul</hi> may be the better preſerved; it is a bright Diamond of Heaven, a ſpark of the very Divinity, and a Ray of the Divine Glory, ſet for a time in the Foil of the Fleſh, til it pleaſeth God to take it to himſelf, and keep it for ever in his Cabinet. O let not thy <hi>Soul,</hi> that tranſparent Diamond, be an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament for the Devils Finger, when it may ſit at the Right Hand of God, where there are Pleaſures for evermore. Thy <hi>Soul</hi> is the Purchaſe of Chriſt, and bought with no leſs than the Blood of the Only Begotten Son of God: then ſell not that for a Triſle which coſt thy Saviour ſo great a Price. It is better to enjoy the Riches of Eternity, than to purchaſe that which is but Vanity, for a moment. If thy Body be diſtempered, then thou requireſt Phiſick, if it be wounded, thou ſendeſt for a <hi>Chirurgeon;</hi> if naked, it muſt have Cloaths; and if hungred, it muſt have Food; for theſe thou ſhouldſt depend upon God, for he knoweth all theſe Things are neceſſary, and will give ſo much as is convenient of them to thee. But when thy poor Soul is ſick of Sin, hath wounds of the Spirit, is ſtript of its Innocence, and ſtarved for Grace, no Regard is given thereunto, not conſidering, that though thou uſeſt humane Helps, yet it is God that gives the Bleſſing, and is the Phiſitian both of <hi>Soul</hi> and <hi>Body.</hi> That Soul which acts the Part of a faithful Servant to the Lord, ſhall have a double Reward, the Crown of a <hi>Saint,</hi> and of a <hi>Sufferer.</hi> The <hi>Soul</hi> is Spiritual, but Sin makes it Carnal; the <hi>Soul</hi> is Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, ſin is the Death of the <hi>Soul,</hi> and being contaminated therewith, it makes us die unto Grace, and to live in Grief: the <hi>Soul</hi> is noble, but ſin makes it ignoble<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>Soul</hi> is Lord, but ſin inſlaves it: the <hi>Soul</hi> is Soveraign, ſin brings it into ſubjection: the <hi>Soul</hi> is God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, ſin makes it beaſtial: the <hi>Soul</hi> is the Spouſe of God, ſin makes it the <hi>Strumpet</hi> of the Devil: the <hi>Soul</hi> is the Jewel of God, ſin caſts it into the Devils Fire: the <hi>Soul</hi> is a Free-born Citizen of Heaven, ſin keeps it in perpetual Impriſonment: the <hi>Soul</hi> is Gods Purchaſe, ſin cheats God of his due, and the <hi>Soul</hi> of Eternal Bliſs. Wouldſt thou be truely perfect, <hi>Love God with all thy Heart, and thy Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as thy ſelf.</hi> Let thine Eye be always upon God and thy ſelf, and thou ſhalt never ſee him without Goodneſs, nor thy ſelf without Miſery<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> none ſhall ſee God ſo much as he is viſible, neither ſhall any love God ſo much as he is amiable. He that doth not covet to love God more and more, can never love him enough, to whom
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:105161:16"/>God is all in all, the World, and all the Delights of it ought to be nothing at all. Let us be what God will, ſo we be but his, and let us not be what we will our ſelves againſt the Will of God. In the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God there is nothing little enough to be rejected. And to meditate much upon God is good, but the <hi>Souls</hi> great Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is Vertue, and it conſiſts in much loving of him: he to whom alone is pleaſing, is diſpleaſed at nothing but that which diſpleaſeth God in Divine Matters: a generous <hi>Soul</hi> finds greateſt Content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in believing things moſt difficult; all our Actions take their value from their Conformity to the Will of God. Love and Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing are the greateſt Duties we owe to God, they being the two Cauſes for which he dyed for us: he that neglects his own Will, complies beſt with Gods Will. So love thy Neighbour here upon Earth, as thou mayſt enjoy his Love in Heaven: thou canſt not love thy Neighbour too much, but thou mayſt make too much ſhew of thy Love to him; one great Argument of our Love to our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, is to bear with his Imperfections; we ſhould never endure to hear any more evil ſpoken of him than of our ſelves; we ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver undervalue any Perſon; the Workman loveth not that his Work ſhould be deſpiſed in his Preſence eſpecially: wherefore beware, for God is preſent every where, and every Man and Woman in the World are his Work. It is a Spiritual Injuſtice to deſire co know the Secrets of others; and to conceal our own. We ought not to love our Neighbour only becauſe he is good, or becauſe we hope he will be ſo, but becauſe God hath commanded us ſo to do: In ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Duties, we ſhould ſpeak little, think much, and do more: it is a great evil not to do good: the Juſt man never dies unprepared; for he is prepared for Death who perſeveres in Juſtice to the End. <hi>Confidence in an unfaithful man, in time of trouble, is like a brooken Tooth, or a Foot out of Joynt:</hi> as he that taketh away a Garment in cold weather: and as Vinegar is upon Nitre ſo is he that ſingeth Songs to one that hath a heavy Heart: it is no ſhame to be poor, though ſome count it acrime; Nature brought us ſo into the World, and ſo we muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn: doſt thou want things that are neceſſary, grumble not, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance it was neceſſary thou ſhouldſt want them: however, if thou ſeekeſt them, let it be by a lawful Remedy or Meanes. If God do not bleſs thy Endeavours, yet do thou bleſs him, that knoweth what is beſt for thee. Thou art God's Patient, preſcribe not to thy Phyſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ian; art thou caluminated, examine thy own Conſcience: if thou findeſt it ſpotted, thou haſt a juſt Correction; if not guilty,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:105161:16"/>thou haſt a very fair Inſtruction; uſe both, and ſo ſhalt thou diſtill <hi>Honey</hi> out of <hi>Gall,</hi> and make to thy ſelf a ſecret Friend of an open Enemy; <hi>if thy Enemy be hungry, give him Bread; if thirſty, give him Drink;</hi> thou thereby ſhalt heap Coals of Fire upon his Head, and a Reward into thy own boſom. Charity makes God our Deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, for the Poor are his Receivers. Haſt thou an Eſtate, &amp; wouldſt increaſe it, devide thy Riches to the Poor; theſe Seeds that are ſcattered do bring forth their Increaſe; but ſuch as are hoarded up, they dye: Correction without Inſtruction makes the Maſter a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and the Servant a Novice: That man is a compleat Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour that can ſubdue his own Paſſions: faithful are the wounds of a Friend, but the Kiſſes of an Enemy are deceitful. Arm thy ſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a profeſt Adverſary; but he that diſſembleth Frindſhip, ſtrikes beyond a Caution, and wounds above a Cure: from the one thou mayſt deliver thy ſelf, but from the other, <hi>Good Lord, deliver thee. A man that flatttreth his Neighbour, ſpreadeth a Net for his feet:</hi> the <hi>Touchſtone</hi> tryeth <hi>Gold,</hi> and <hi>Gold</hi> tryeth <hi>Men:</hi> virtue muſt be the guide of all Qualities, otherwiſe the Profeſſors thereof are undone. As the Servants of God are known by their two Vertues, <hi>Humiliation</hi> and <hi>Charity;</hi> ſo the Servants of the Devil are known by their oppoſite Vices, <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Cruelty.</hi> The beſt way to keep good Acts in memory, is to refreſh them with new ones: to boaſt is but vain, ſince the greateſt Conquerour is but the meaſure of his own ſhadow, and ſhall find it no longer than it was before his Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: believe not <hi>Soothſayers,</hi> for Prophecies are never underſtood till they are accompliſhed. The World is a wide Priſon, and every Day is an Execution day; our Stomacks are very common Sepulchres of Birds, Beaſts, &amp; Fiſh; they all die to feed us. Lord, with how many Deaths are our Lives patcht up, and how full of Death is the whole Life of Man; beware of too much Drink; where <hi>Drunkenneſs</hi> is, and doth reign, Reaſon is baniſhed into Exile, Vertue is made a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and God himſelf is become an Enemy; <hi>Blaſpemies</hi> are account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Wit,</hi> and <hi>Oaths</hi> are <hi>Rhetorick,</hi> and <hi>Secrets</hi> are made open <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations.</hi> Whoſoever will arrive at a new Life, muſt paſs by the old Death of the old; he that is truly humbled, never thinks him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf wronged; the good Man is well contented with a moderate <hi>Estate,</hi> not ſo much taking notice of thoſe that have more, as thoſe that have leſs in this World, than himſelf. He that moſt mortifies his <hi>natural Inclinations,</hi> receiveth moſt <hi>Spiritual Inſpirations:</hi> to ſhun the accidental Troubles of this Life, is to meditate often upon <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:105161:17"/>It's the great misfortune of man to deſire thoſe things which he ſhould only uſe. To have a deſire not to be poor, &amp; to receive the <hi>Inconveniences</hi> of it, is too great Ambition; for, it is to deſire the Honour of <hi>Poverty,</hi> &amp; the Commodity of Wealth. There is no way happily to end a true Spiritual Life, better than dayly to begin it. He that would have a Part with Jeſus glorified, muſt firſt take part with Chriſt crucified: we ſhould live in this preſent Evil World, as if our Souls were in Heaven, and our Bodies in the Grave. In the death of our <hi>Paſſions</hi> conſiſts the Life of our Souls. It is not <hi>Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> to acknowledge our ſelves miſerable, that is only to be a <hi>Beaſt:</hi> but it is <hi>Humility</hi> to deſire that others ſhould eſteem us ſo. There is no reaſon to be given for the Fault we commit in Sin; for the Fault would not be Sin, if it were not againſt Reaſon. Vertues have not their full <hi>Growth,</hi> but when they have Deſires to bring forth Advantage; which like <hi>Spiritual Seeds,</hi> ſerve to bring forth and produce new degrees of Virtues. We ſhould never ſpeak of God, or the Things which concern his Service, careleſly, or by way of Common Diſcourſe or Entertainment, but always with a great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect and humble mind. We ſhould fear the Judgments of God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Diſcouragement, and encourage our ſelves without Preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The ready way for the Soul to have Peace with its ſelf, is to obtain his Peace with God; we may perform many Holy Actions, and yet not pleaſe God, if we neglect to do what he requires of us, no more than a <hi>Painter,</hi> in repreſenting an <hi>Eagle,</hi> pleaſeth him that deſired a <hi>Bee.</hi> Let us never look on our Croſſes, but through the Croſs of Jeſus Chriſt, thereby we ſhall find them pleaſant, and have freſh Deſires to be afflicted; Deſire to obtain the Love of God, makes us to meditate, but that Love once obtained, makes us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template. <hi>The Fear of the Lord is the Beginning of Wiſdom; and the Price of Wiſdom is above Rubies. Oh let my Prayers be ſet before thee as Incenſe, and the lifting up of my Hands be as the Evening Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, O Lord, my Strength, and moſt mighty Redeemer.</hi> Oh my Soul! What fearful tremblings are theſe that have ſeized upon thee now? So that the Thoughts of God, that have been, and ought to be thy greateſt Comforts, are now become thy Amazement: Whence is this miſerable Altaration, that thou muſt behold nothing but Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Father of Mercies, and Anger in the Fountain of Love? What hath provoked him that delights to ſpare, to be reſolved to puniſh? Surely my Sins are very many, for it is not a few that will inſenſe him, and they have more than ordinary Aggravations; for
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:105161:17"/>he is not ſo highly diſpleaſed at ſmall Offences, and certainly I have often committed them, and long continued in them; for he begins not to frown upon the firſt Miſdemeanour. Alas! Alas! the Cauſe is too apparent, my Sins are both very many, and exceeding great; frequently repeated with heynous Circumſtances, and of long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance; I have deſpiſed Mercy, &amp; now am like to feel Judgment, moſt miſerable Wreth that I am. I have tired out the Patience of a long-ſuffering Father, and have run away from the Embraces of a Loving Saviour, and have rejected the Offers of a moſt indulgent Holy Spirit; ſo that now I fear I have ſtopt up the Fountain of his Mercy, and unſealed the Treaſure of his Vengeance; and I ought to wonder how God could ſpare me ſo long, then why he ſhould ſtrike me now, ſince many have been cut off for fewer and leſſer ſins. I ſee that I have deſerved moſt juſtly to ſuffer the worſt of Evils. And therefore ſhall eſteem it an incomparable Favour to be only corrected with Temporal Afflictions, if I might be ſo excuſed; but it is a fearful thing to fall into the Hands of the Living God. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, O Lord, my Fleſh trembleth for very Fear of thee, and I am afraid of thy moſt heavy Judgments, yet I know no way to eſcape them. To deny my Sins, were great <hi>Impudence,</hi> and to Excuſe them, will be Apparent <hi>Hypocriſy,</hi> and to be concealed, is impoſſible; to be found intollerable; I am miſerably confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but was never any in this ſad Caſe before, that I might receive ſome Advice and Comfort from them? Yes ſurely, the Church hath preſented me with a King and a Prophet, both dear to God, whoſe Fears were greater, though their Sins were leſs, and their danger not ſo great as mine. Yet theſe in the midſt of their Fear, conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Sins as the only Cauſe of their Evils, and accordingly they freely confeſſed them, bitterly lamented, and exceedingly humbled themſelves for them, not ſtriving ſo much to avoid them in the Puniſhment, as to obtain the Pardon of their Offences; knowing that the guilt once removed, thou wouldſt totally ſpare them, or gently chaſtiſe them for their good; where they rendred themſelves up into thy Hands, rather aggravating, than extenuating their Sins, and yet humbly begging that they might be corrected in Mercy, and they found the Benefit of it. Go to then, O my Soul, and do thou likewiſe, thou haſt occaſioned Gods Wrath by the Breach of his moſt holy Laws. O do not increaſe it by miſtruſting the bleſſed Goſpel; thou haſt forſaken him by Sin, do not run from him by Deſpair; for the faſter that thou runneſt from his Mercy, the ſooner thou ſhalt be ſure to meet with his <hi>Juſtice;</hi> delay no longer, but go
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:105161:18"/>in before he ſends for thee; accuſe thy ſelf before thou art <hi>Indicted;</hi> and confeſs thy Sins freely before the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> be called out againſt thee; paſs ſentence on thy ſelf before the <hi>Judge</hi> come to <hi>condemn</hi> thee. I cannot expect wholly to eſcape; but it will be a great Favour if I meet only with a Sickneſs inſtead of Death; Loſſes in my Eſtate, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of looſing my God, and my Soul both, for ever. I will not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſire my Heavenly Father altogether to lay aſide his Rod, but only to uſe it gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly, that I may by this ſmart be <hi>warn'd</hi> againſt thoſe future ſins that would bring me to utter Ruine. O Lord, rather chaſtiſe me than diſ-inherit me, and thoſe Stripes ſhall be welcome which come in an exchange for Eternal Torments. For thou who doſt change thy <hi>Sword</hi> into a <hi>Rod,</hi> I hope will be ſo compaſſionate in thy <hi>Afflictions,</hi> that I ſhall only feel what my deſtempered Soul needs to recover it, and my Fleſh and Spirit cannot bear; not what my Sins deſerve, and thy Juſtice might exact; wherefore I will no longer hide my ſins, but by an humble &amp; hearty Confeſſion will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that I hate them more than I fear to fall into thy moſt merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Hands: and I hope hereafter, that I ſhall ſo fear to offend, that I ſhall be freed from thoſe ſad Expectations of thy heavy Wrath, which Wiſdom God grant me, for my Saviour Jeſus Chriſt's Sake. He that hath a Requeſt to make, that is conſiderable, to an Earthly King, muſt not approach without a Preſent in his Hand: but my great Requeſt is to the King of Kings, to whoſe Laws I have been diſobedient, falſe to his Government, refractory to his Summons, and ungrateful to his former Favours: and what can I offer him that needs nothing? and what can I give him, whoſe both my ſelf, and all that I have are? His Favour inheed is ſo ſweet, ſo deſirable, and ſo univerſal a Comprehenſion of all happineſs, that I could free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly give all I have, or may procure, for the Purchaſe of it. But the whole World is Vanity to him, neither can ſuch Triffles blind his Eyes, or bind his Hands, buy his Mercy to the Unworthy, or avert his Judgments from the Sinner. I would methinks expoſe my Body to the ſharpeſt Torments, my Soul to the heavieſt Sorrows and my Life to the cruelleſt of Tyrants, and would account it a happy pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe if I were ſure of his Everlaſting Mercies afterwards. But it coſt more to redeem a Soul; I can give nothing but what is his al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, and I can ſuffer nothing but what I have deſerved: What then? O where ſhall I have a Peace-Offering which may not be deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: I am told that there is nothing more acceptable than a Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Heart. 'Tis ſtrange, Can a Heart polluted with the Guilt, and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:105161:18"/>inflamed with the Power of Sin, ſlow to begin, and unable to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form any thing that is good, but vigorous to deſire, and unwearied to purſue all evil. Can a Heart ſhaken with Fears, torn to pieces with Terrours, and even a Terrour to it ſelf, miſerable and poor, blind and naked, can this Heart be a fit Sacrifice for ſo Glorious and All-ſeeing, ſo Holy and Pure a God? Can he like that whieh I ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor my ſelf? Alas! it cannot be. But let me recall that raſh &amp; haſty word, for he hath ſaid it who beſt knows what will pleaſe himſelf; and if he vallues it, then it is worthy; for the true worth of any thing is to be judged by his Eſteemation of it: who knows but ſuch a broken Heart may be a greater Evidence of his Power and Mercy, a fitter Inſtrument of his Praiſe and Glory, a plainer Table to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe his Grace, and draw his Image on, than any other. Such a Heart I have, and if this will ſerve, I am happy; I will give it free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to thee, O Lord, who deſpiſeſt not the meaneſt Gifts, if there be ſincerity in the Giver. It was broken before with Fear, but now it will be diſſolved with Love. I am aſhamed it is no better, but thy Mercy is the greater in accepting it, and it will become better by being thine. Oh how am I filled with Admiration on the Freeneſs and Fullneſs of thy Mercies, in compariſon of which the greateſt humane Compaſſion is, and ſeems to be Cruelty. I dare proclaim it, that in thee are all the Mercies in the World united, and thou art Mercy it ſelf in the higheſt Degree. If my Diſobedience, and my Negligence, Contempts, and Ingratitudes could have ſeperated thee from thy Mercy, I had now met thee in thy Fury, taking Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance without Pitty; for I have ſeemed to live as if I had deſigned to dare thee to turn thy ſelf away from me, and to try thy utmoſt Patience; the leaſt part of which buſineſs would have turned my beſt Friends in the World againſt me; but behold the Mercies of my God continue ſtill. O let me have the ſhame of an ungrateful Sinner, and let thy Name have the Glory of an inexpreſſable Pitty, even to thoſe who are almoſt aſhamed to ask Pardon? yea, let me, to whom thou haſt ſhewed ſo much Compaſſion, have the Honour to be an <hi>Inſtance</hi> of thy Goodneſs to all the World. And have I ſuch a Father, Why then do I lye ſtill with this Load of Guilt upon my Soul? And with this heavy Burthen of Sorrow upon my Spirit? What do I get by theſe Complaints, but waſte my Time, and dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble my Miſery by ſad Reflections? I can neither have Help from my ſelf, nor any Creature, but my Father alone, to whom Mercies are as proper as Miſeries are to me; and if I through Fear and Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:105161:19"/>ſit ſtill here and ſtarve, I ſhew not ſo much Pitty to my ſelf as he would have for me, if he ſaw my diſtreſs. Wherefore I will ariſe and go to him, though I think that I ſhall ſcarce have the face to ask him more, ſince I ſpent the laſt ſo ill; I ſhall be aſhamed to tell him how baſe I have been: but as I was not aſhamed when I did evil, ſo I muſt have ſhame when I ſuffer the ſhame of its deſert, I will go bathed with Tears, bluſhing for ſhame, accuſing my ſelf, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lying on the Bowels of a Father, and will beg only ſo much Mercy as may baniſh deſpair; and if I may have this, will be content, tho I be not entertained with aſſurance and certain Expectations; for the leaſt favourable Look is more than I have deſerved: yet behold, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the firſt ſight of the returning Prodigal, who came unſent for driven home by his own Miſeries, his tender Father runs to meet him, takes the Words out of his Mouth, and receives him with all the Demonſtrations of his Love, and the Carreſſes of his dear Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections: and is my God leſs merciful; he who hath invited me ſo often, and promiſed me ſo largely; I have done ill to ſtay ſo long; but I will go now, low in my Deſires, and high in my Expectations, ſorrowing for mine Offences, and begging his Mercies; and I hope, though I carry no merits of my own to his Juſtice; yet I carry miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y enough to make his <hi>Bowels</hi> of <hi>Compaſſion</hi> yearn upon me, &amp; then I cannot periſh. Is it poſſible I ſhould be all this while deluded ſo groſly, as to imagine <hi>my Eyes to be opened, my Ways direct and full of Light;</hi> when indeed <hi>my Eyes are ſhut, my feet are wrong, and my Mind is overſpred with Aegyptian Darkneſs, of a ſtupid Ignorance.</hi> Thy Word, O Lord, is a Light to my Feet, and a Lanthorn to my Pathes; not only to ſhew me which is the right way, but to let me know when I am in the wrong. But I have given my ſelf to falſe Guides, who leaſt I ſhould enquire after the right way, would never acquaint me that I was wandring from it; had I followed them ſtill, I had ſtumbled ere this on the threſhold of <hi>Hell,</hi> whil'ſt I expected to have arrived at the <hi>Gates of Heaven.</hi> O bleſſed be thy Name, I now ſee that I have been ſtraying from the <hi>Fountain of all true Happineſs,</hi> and have been in vain ſeeking Content where it is not to be found, till the Diſappointment drives me to ſeek it where it is to be had: if I had not been a Stanger to my own Heart, I had not been ſo far out of the right way: but I have ſuppoſed my ſelf to be clear, only becauſe I never conſidered wherein I was guilty, and have flattered my ſelf with the pleaſing Thoughts of my own <hi>Innocence,</hi> ſo that I have been ſo ſecure, as if I had been really guiltleſs; I have been
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:105161:19"/>glad to ſpare my ſelf, and have flattered my ſelf with the pleaſing <hi>Thoughts</hi> of my own <hi>Ignorance,</hi> I have been glad to ſpare my ſelf of a further Enquiry, moſt fooliſhly accounting this a Peace which was no other but want of a ſenſe of my own danger. I find my chief <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign</hi> hath been to ſeem to be good, and to perſwade my ſelf that I was ſo, that I might be the more at quiet in the ways of Evil, and might not be accuſed of my own Conſcience, and allaramed by the <hi>moſt dreadful Threatnings;</hi> which I ſuppoſed did not belong to me. But alas! how miſerable would the end of that ſelf-deceit have been. For thou, O my God, didſt ſee, and wouldſt have condemned me for all my <hi>Blaſphemous Thoughts,</hi> and <hi>Repinings</hi> againſt thee; my <hi>malitious</hi> and <hi>envious Thoughts</hi> againſt thee and my <hi>Neighbour;</hi> thou heardſt all thoſe vain and filth words that I uttered with my Mouth; thoſe <hi>deceitful, unjuſt, and cruel uncharitable Works</hi> which I committed with my Hands thou ſaweſt; yea, all that <hi>Formality</hi> and <hi>Hypocriſy, Ambition</hi> and <hi>Pride, Luſt</hi> and <hi>Covetuouſneſs</hi> that lay in the ſecret Corners of my Heart, was apparent in thy ſight, and what did it avail me not to ſee them; thy <hi>Vengeance</hi> would have once as certainly, and more terribly, becauſe it was not expected. It is ſtrange I ſhould not ſee this vaſt heap before; but ſurely I have ſhut my eyes wilfully, leſt I ſhould diſcern that which I was loath to believe, and unwilling to amend, but now I ſee my Inquities by thy Mercy, and believe I have offended thee as much by my <hi>Hypocriſy</hi> in the concealing them, as by my <hi>Diſobedience</hi> in committing them; therefore I will ingeniouſly confeſs, becauſe the <hi>graciouſneſs of thy Nature, the truth of thy Promiſes, and the Satisfaction of the Lord Jeſus,</hi> are ſufficient to procure a Pardon for me, who dare ſo truſt in thy <hi>Mercy</hi> ſo far, as to become my own Accuſer. Yea, my God, ſince thou haſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſo graciouſly convinced me of the <hi>Evil</hi> and <hi>Damage</hi> of thoſe Courſes I have taken, I will not reſt in a bare <hi>Confeſſion</hi> that I am in the <hi>Wrong,</hi> but <hi>by thy Grace,</hi> will turn me into the <hi>Right Way,</hi> and will utterly forſake all theſe my <hi>Follies:</hi> thy <hi>Mercy</hi> indeed, is <hi>great enough</hi> to forgive me upon my <hi>Humble Acknowledgments;</hi> but to live in my Sin, is as inconſiſtent with my <hi>Happineſs,</hi> as it is with thy <hi>holy Laws.</hi> Therefore, O my Soul, he that deſires thy <hi>Felicity,</hi> will not forgive the old <hi>Score,</hi> unleſs thou ceaſe to run further in Debt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Doſt thou not ſee, that whil'ſt thou goeſt on in Sin, thou art in the <hi>Way</hi> unto <hi>Eternal Death;</hi> and beſide, art already dead to all Divine Comforts, as to the ſenſe of them, and Buried alive in Luſts and Pleaſures; thy Fleſh intombs thy precious Soul, that is thus made
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:105161:20"/>wretched, and the <hi>Grave-Cloths</hi> of vile Affections, binds the Hand and Foot from moving towards God, or breathing in the pure Air of Heavenly Meditations, and canſt thou like to ſtay in this filthy Place ſtill, when thou didſt not ſee thy Miſery; no wonder if thou countedſt this Dungeon and Vault, a Pallace; but now thou muſt abhor it, when Jeſus calls, and ſaith, <hi>Lazarus, come forth.</hi> Doſt thou find, the more thou followeſt theſe, the leſs thou loveſt God, &amp; haſt ſeldom any Converſe with him, ſlower Motions towards him, and meaner Thoughts of him; return then from theſe Evil Paths, for now thou knoweſt the dead are there; do not only ſeek a Pardon from him, but deſire a Communion with him, who is thy Strength and Life, thy Joy and Happineſs, and will be glad of thy Recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; that forgetting all thy Unworthineſs formerly, he will make thee happy hereafter; there is nothing can hinder thee, unleſs thou loveſt thy Sins ſo well, that thou wilt not forſake them; and careſt ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle for God, that thou hadſt rather dye without him, than live with him Holily here, and Eternally Happily hereafter; it had been well with my Soul, if all this while my ſafty had been equal to my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence; for none ever thought themſelves more ſecure, tho there was no other ground for it, but only becauſe I was not reſolved to take the pains not to behold my Danger. I have multiplyed my Tranſgreſſions, and lived in Sins unamended, yea, un-repented of, and therefore have had the drawn Sword of <hi>Divine Vengeance</hi> hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over my guilty Head, by the ſlender thread of my uncertain Life, which every thing can ſnap in ſunder; yet have I wilfully ſhut mine eyes, chooſing rather to feel the Eternal Smart of it, than to behold the dreadful ſight which would have long time terrified me into an amendment, and have ſnatcht me from under the approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ruine. What prodigious Folly hath ſeized on me? What ſtupid Lazines hath benummed me? Are the Pains of eſcaping, greater than the Pains of Suffering? Or will the Blow be the lighter, becauſe I reſolve neither to ſee it, nor avoid it? Awake, my Soul, while there is a Poſſibility to prevent thy Ruine; thy Sins are ſo numerous and ſo hainous, that thou canſt not be ignorant of them, the Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of Gods Wrath are ſo plain and poſitive, that thou mayſt ſee plainly, that they aim at thee; thy Conſcience cryes ſo loud, that thou canſt not but hear it, and Gods Holy Spirit pleads ſtill ſo powerfully, that thou muſt take ſo much Pains to exclude theſe Friends as would ſerve to turn out thy Enemies: ſurely God gave me not Wit and Underſtanding, to make a plauceable Cover for the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:105161:20"/>eyes of my <hi>Conſcience,</hi> or to contrive <hi>Bulwarks</hi> of Excuſes, to entrench my ſins in ſafety, and yet I, unhappy Wretch, have been ingenious in nothing ſo much as in plotting the Ruine of my precious Soul, and deſigning to periſh undiſturbed: behold, and bluſh to ſee how, and where holy <hi>David</hi> lies covered with <hi>Shame,</hi> and drowned in his <hi>Tears,</hi> quite overwhelmed with <hi>Sorrow,</hi> not able, through <hi>Fear</hi> and <hi>Sorrow,</hi> to take his Eyes off that one Offence, whil'ſt thou, a far greater <hi>Sinner,</hi> art careleſs and unconverted; he ſets his ſins before his <hi>own Face,</hi> and God he throws them behind his <hi>Back:</hi> when the ſight of them will not conduce to the obtaining of my <hi>Pardon,</hi> but the <hi>Aggravation</hi> of my <hi>Eternal Miſery,</hi> the ſight of them indeed is <hi>moſt unpleaſant,</hi> the Object <hi>odious</hi> and <hi>ungrateful,</hi> but the Benefit will <hi>moſt abundantly</hi> recompence the Trouble; and if I behold them now ſo as to repent of them, I ſhall ſee them no more for ever; I will <hi>Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate</hi> therefore this holy Man, and ever view the <hi>Guilt</hi> and <hi>Danger</hi> of them, that I may humbly confeſs them with <hi>Sorrow,</hi> and obtain a <hi>Pardon</hi> for them, my wretched Heart hath taken pleaſure in the <hi>Committing them,</hi> and it ſhall have Vexation in <hi>Reflecting on them,</hi> for I will not take my eyes off from them, till the horrid <hi>Aſpect</hi> of my grievous Iniquities have humbled my Soul for them, and turned my Heart againſt them. O Bleſſed Jeſus, that knoweſt the <hi>Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> of all, thy <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Commands</hi> to <hi>Repentance</hi> to all men, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks ſeems to be peculiarly directed to me, who have neglected this moſt neceſſary Duty: hitherto thou, O Lord ſeeſt my Danger, and pittieſt my Approaching Ruine; I Bow my Head and Heart, and neither can, or dare diſobey ſo gracious and loving Advice, ſo uſeful and neceſſary a Warning: thy bare Words hath been ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to command Obedience from me, who do expect Eternal Salvation by thee, but thou art pleaſed further to convince me; I do believe, deareſt Jeſus, the Benefit is great, if I ſhall turn now while thy <hi>Grace</hi> is offered ſo freely to all People; I know the danger is dreadful, if I delay any longer, ſince 'tis certain, that thy Kingdom ſhall come, but uncertain, now ſoon either Death ſhall Arreſt me, or Judgment ſurpriſe me in ſuch Delays: I have great cauſe to bleſs thy Name, that neither of theſe have happened yet unto me, though I have even excluded thee out of my Heart, and entertained my Sins there; yet Lord, thou calleſt on me ſtill, and now I am ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king what haſt I can. O remember not how long I have ſtaid, but conſider how little time I have left, and by the help of thy <hi>Grace,</hi> make my Work ſhort and eaſie, proportionable to my Time and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:105161:21"/>Strength. I confeſs that I knew before, but I never conſidered it till now, and now I dare not ſtay, but through thy help, I come. O do not caſt me off, for thy <hi>Mercies</hi> ſake. Oh my Soul, thou art ſurely ſeized with a ſtrange <hi>Diſtemper,</hi> which reſiſts the <hi>Efficacy</hi> of the choiſeſt Remedies; the <hi>Plaiſter</hi> which cures others, doth not avail me; I confeſs my Offences every day on my bended Knees, but my <hi>Faith</hi> is <hi>Weak;</hi> my <hi>Hope Wavering;</hi> my ſenſe of <hi>Gods Love very ſmall,</hi> ſo that I am almoſt tempted to live like thoſe that are unconverted, and unconcerned whether they ſin, or no; becauſe I find no Benefit by all my <hi>Humiliations;</hi> and this <hi>Temptation</hi> had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed, if I had not ſeen, that ſince others receive ſome Advantage by theſe meanes, the fault is in me, and not in them, nor in the God whom I Serve, he cannot deny his <hi>Promiſes,</hi> falſifie his <hi>Word,</hi> nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject thoſe when they come, who come upon his <hi>Courteous Invitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> O where then is this accurſed thing that reſtrains Gods <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,</hi> blaſts my Endeavours, and puts me upon Injurious Thoughts againſt <hi>Heaven,</hi> &amp; <hi>Atheiſtical Reſolutions</hi> of totally neglecting thoſe <hi>Holy Things:</hi> the Matter of my Duty is good, for God commands it; the Benefit is great, for many have found it to be ſo; but, Is it done in a right manner? The failing may be there: I have been more careful to kneel reverently, look ſadly, ſigh grievouſly, and tell the Almighty a <hi>Story</hi> of my <hi>Sinful Life,</hi> with <hi>Addreſſes</hi> becomming a <hi>Penitent,</hi> but this comes far ſhort of what God requires, even a <hi>Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Heart,</hi> and a <hi>Contrite Spirit;</hi> for I have been ſo concerned to ſeem ſorrowful, that I have not endeavoured really to be ſo. O my God, thou that ſearcheſt the Heart, and tryeſt the Reins, thou haſt ſeen my Heart untouch't in the midſt of theſe <hi>Pretences;</hi> I have not been ſmitten with the <hi>Odiouſueſs</hi> of my Sins to thee, nor the <hi>Danger</hi> to me, and therefore I have not fully renounced them, nor yet abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely returned to thee and thy Ways, and therefore thou haſt not bleſſed my <hi>Confeſſions,</hi> which have been rather looked upon by me, as an Indulgence to go on, ſince my former were ſo eaſily pardoned, than an Ingagement to forſake mine Iniquities; but now I ſee my Vileneſs in making ſo ſlight Addreſſes for ſo great a Favour; I diſcern my Folly to cheat my ſelf of ſo conſiderable a Bleſſing, and my Sloath to ſlip ſo many fair Opportunities by my deceitful <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>havior</hi> before thee. O Lord, I have deceived my ſelf, I am hugely aſhamed, that having offended ſo dear and loving a Father, I have not been really concerned more, and having ſo gracious a God to turn to, I am yet ſo far diſtant from him; if I want Pardon or Peace,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:105161:21"/>the blame muſt be upon my own Negligence, for thou art apt to give, and ready to forgive, long before thou puniſheſt Sinners, but ſoon intreated to receive <hi>Preſents,</hi> &amp; doſt moſt joyfully lay aſide thy Reſolutions of <hi>Judgments,</hi> when we promiſe our Purpoſe of <hi>Amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> O my Soul, will not this real Goodneſs of thy God ſhame thy <hi>Hyppocriſy?</hi> Will it not pierce thine Heart to ſee whom thou haſt offended, and thaw thy Hopes to behold him whom thou art turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to: his <hi>Holineſs</hi> is mixed with <hi>Long-ſuffering,</hi> his <hi>Juſtice</hi> with <hi>Mercy,</hi> his <hi>Decrees</hi> allayed with <hi>Limitations,</hi> and is it fit to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach him without <hi>Love</hi> or <hi>Fear, Hopes</hi> or <hi>Deſires, Gratitude</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Admiration?</hi> Or, Is the <hi>Forgiveneſs</hi> too mean a <hi>Favour,</hi> that it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves no more <hi>Hearty Applications;</hi> ſure enough mine <hi>Hyppocriſy</hi> hath hindred my <hi>Pardon,</hi> wherefore I begin to deteſt it, and hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I will look more to the <hi>Diſpoſition</hi> of my <hi>Heart</hi> than the <hi>Poſture</hi> of my <hi>Body;</hi> I will ſet him before me whoſe Love I have abuſed, and whoſe Patience I have tried, who is ſo gracious as to ſpare me, and ſo willing to be Reconciled to a moſt ungrateful Wretch, that when I come to him, I may have my <hi>Eyes</hi> filled with Tears, and my <hi>Cheeks</hi> with Bluſhes, and my <hi>Heart</hi> with Sorrow; I will remembe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> who I am that go ſo, that my <hi>Heart</hi> may be hum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e, and what I go for, that I may be earneſt, and who I go to, that I may be full of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Hope,</hi> ſo tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> my <hi>Addreſſes</hi> may not be in vain, but that all theſe gracious <hi>Attributes</hi> may be made good unto me for Jeſu, Sake, to whom be Glory for ever.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Thomas Brownings<hi>'s Prayer</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O Lord, prepare my unprepared and ſinful <hi>Heart</hi> by thy <hi>Holy</hi> and <hi>Bleſſed Spirit</hi> to Pray unto thee; for Jeſus Chriſt his Sake, pour down into my <hi>Heart</hi> thy Spirit of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>race, Supplication,</hi> and <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation;</hi> good God, do away mine <hi>Iniquities,</hi> and remember my <hi>Tranſgreſſens</hi> no more, help me to pour out my Soul before thee, under a deepſence of, and a true ſorrow for all my Sins which I have moſt wickedly and grieviouſly committed againſt thy Divine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty from time to time, help me to pray with the Spirit, and with Underſtanding, let thy Spirit help my <hi>Infirmities</hi> with <hi>Sighs</hi> and <hi>Groans</hi> that cannot be expreſſed; ſtrike my Heart with an Awe and Dread of thy <hi>Maieſty;</hi> help me to approach thy Preſence with <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erence,</hi> a <hi>Godly Shame</hi> and <hi>Holy Trembling<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> there is no ſecret
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:105161:22"/>Thoughts afar off; help me to confeſs my Sins with a true <hi>Sorrow</hi> for the ſame, help me to depart from all Iniquity, that it may not be my Ruine, let me hate all <hi>Sin</hi> with a perfect <hi>Hatred,</hi> and avoid the very Appearance of Evil; let me no longer regard any <hi>Iniquity</hi> in my <hi>Heart,</hi> leaſt it prove my undoing, knowing that the very Hope of the <hi>Hyppocrite</hi> ſtall periſh, but work in me a <hi>Godly Sorrow</hi> for my ſin, which may cauſe a true <hi>Repentance</hi> unto <hi>Salvation,</hi> never to be repented of, and for Jeſus ſake, accept a <hi>Morning Sacrifice</hi> of <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Praiſe,</hi> which I do deſire at this time in all ſincerity to offer to thy Divine Majeſty, humbly begging the Aſſiſtance of thy <hi>Grace.</hi> O Eternal, Almighty, and moſt Glorious Lord God, in whom I Live. Move, and have my Being, thou art the Mighty Majeſty of <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi> thou art the great <hi>Creator</hi> and <hi>Governour</hi> of all Things, who didſt make all Things by the Word of thy Power, and doſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the ſame by thy <hi>Providence,</hi> who art the Omnipotent God, Dwelling in the higheſt Heavens, and haſt Eternity for thy <hi>Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in that Light which is inacceſſable, to whom no mortal Eye can approach, Infinite in all thy Attributes, before whoſe Glorious Preſence the <hi>Angels, Cherubims,</hi> and <hi>Seraphims,</hi> thoſe ſpotleſs Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures do cover their Faces, &amp; the <hi>Elders</hi> do caſt down their Crowns, Worſhipping thee continually; thou art Glorious in Majeſty, Fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in Praiſes, doing Wonders, God over all, Bleſſed for evermore, from Everlaſting to Everlaſting, Infinitely Happy in the Injoyment of thine own Perfections, and needeſt not the Services of any of thy Creatures, and haſt an innumerable Company of Angels, Arch-Angels, Cherubims, Seraphims, with the Spirits of Juſt Men and Women made Perfect; all the Heavenly and Coeleſtial Hoſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually Celebrating thy Praiſe, crying, <hi>Holy, Holy, Holy Lord God Almighty, which Was, which Is, and which is to come.</hi> O where ſhall I appear that am Vile, Sinful, Duſt, and Aſhes? For Jeſus Sake have Mercy upon me, I confeſs that I am very ſinful by Nature, and more vile by Practice, who am of the Seed of Evil Doers, and have been a Tranſgreſſor from the Womb, that I was Conceived in Sin, Brought forth in Iniquity, and my Life hath been as a continued Act of Sinning againſt thee, as if I had been born for no other Purpoſe, but to diſhonour, diſpleaſe, and diſobey the God that Made me, and to deſtroy that Immortal Soul for whom Chriſt dyed, and the Lord world Save: thou haſt been very Gracious and Merciful to me in my Creation and Preſervation; but above all, in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Fountain and Foundation of all my Mercies, and through
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:105161:22"/>whom I have Hopes of <hi>Eternal Salvation.</hi> It is a Faithful Saying, and worthy all <hi>Acceptation, That Jeſus Chriſt came into the World to Save Sinners,</hi> Of whom I am chief, and I am never able ſufficiently to Admire, Adore, and Magnifie thy great Name, for thy Infinite Love in the Lord Jeſus, thy <hi>Mercy, Goodneſs,</hi> and <hi>Condeſcention</hi> hath appeared in this, that thou who art the Mighty Majeſty of <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi> a God of all Power, Omnipotency it ſelf, ſhouldeſt find out a way to reconcile thoſe great <hi>Attributes</hi> of thy <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Juſtice,</hi> through the Blood of thy Onely Begotten Son; that ſo poor, loſt, and undone <hi>Mortals</hi> might be Eternally Saved, and this thou haſt declared unto me Jeſus Chriſt Crucified, and for me, who am leſs than the leaſt of thy <hi>Mercies;</hi> and this thou haſt made known by thy <hi>Holy Goſpel.</hi> O the <hi>Height, Length, Depth,</hi> and <hi>Breadth</hi> of thy Love in Jeſus Chriſt, it is above my <hi>Apprehenſion</hi> and <hi>Comprehenſion,</hi> it is paſt my finding out; l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t it be Matter of <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Praiſe</hi> in the Heavens: and through him thou haſt been pleaſed to afford me the meanes of <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Salvation</hi> in very plentiful manner, thy <hi>Sabboths,</hi> thy <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Ordinances,</hi> thy <hi>Holy</hi> and <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Spirit</hi> to aſſiſt me, the Checks of my own <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and the Light of Nature to inſtruct me, I have had <hi>Line</hi> upon <hi>Line, Precept</hi> upon <hi>Precept,</hi> here a little, and there a little, often hearing a Voice within, and behind me, ſaying, <hi>This is the Way, walk in it.</hi> Thou haſt lengthened out my <hi>Days,</hi> and afforded me a large time to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, in exerciſing thy Patience and Long-ſuffering towards me, I have had large Experience of thy Goodneſs to lead me to an Amendment of Life; and though in all Times, Ages, and Places, thou haſt ſhewed thy ſelf highly diſpleaſed with Sin and Sinners, yet thou haſt been pleaſed to ſpare me; and I have aggravated my Sins with hainous Circumſtances; the Angels when they ſinned, were caſt down, and are reſerved in Everlaſting Chains of Darkneſs, made Monuments of thy <hi>Juſtice, Wrath,</hi> and <hi>Fury,</hi> and there was never any Meanes found out for their Recovery: Jeſus Chriſt took not upon him the Nature of Angels, but the Seed of <hi>Abraham;</hi> my firſt Parents were baniſhed out of <hi>Paradice</hi> for their Tranſgreſſions, and the Old World for their Sin were drownded; <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morhea,</hi> once famous Places, for their Sins, felt, the Divine Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance by Fire from Heaven, and were conſumed with an utter Overthrow, yet thou haſt ſpared me, the chief of Sinners. O Lord, grant that thy <hi>Severity</hi> towards others, and thy <hi>Goodneſs</hi> towards me, may lead me to an Amendment of Life, or how ſhall I eſcape to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:105161:23"/>neglect ſuch great Salvation. O Lord, thou haſt been very gracious unto me, by keeping me <hi>Mercifully</hi> in my <hi>Infancy, Child-hood, Youth, Riper Age, Manhood,</hi> and <hi>Age:</hi> thou haſt taken Care of me, when I took none of my ſelf; I have been <hi>Fed, Cloathed,</hi> and <hi>Led along by thy good Hand of Providence,</hi> thou haſt given me a <hi>Healthy Body,</hi> a <hi>Sound Mind,</hi> and a <hi>Large Memory,</hi> my <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> have been <hi>Cured,</hi> I have been <hi>Fed</hi> both with the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper</hi> and <hi>Nether Springs;</hi> thou haſt not only given me Things convenient for this Life, hut likewiſe the Mercies of <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Salvation</hi> leading to a better Life, even to <hi>Life Everlaſting;</hi> thou haſt preſerved me in <hi>Priſon</hi> beyond my <hi>Deſert,</hi> contrary to my <hi>Expectation,</hi> when the World frowned upon me, and I was forſaken by my <hi>Relations,</hi> then the Lord was a <hi>Sun</hi> to comfort, and a <hi>Shield</hi> to defend me; thou haſt been my preſent Help in time of Trouble, my exceeding great Reward, my All in All, my God Alſufficient, thou haſt compaſſed me about with thy <hi>Salvation, Songs of Deliverance,</hi> thy <hi>Special Favours;</hi> yea, thou haſt prevented me with thy very <hi>Loving Kindneſs;</hi> I have been both Loaded and Cloathed with thy <hi>Mercies,</hi> as with a <hi>Garment,</hi> and they are more in number, the very kinds of them, than I am able to reckon up. O Lord, thou haſt not only given me a <hi>Being,</hi> but a comfortable and well <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> to make me the more fit to Serve thee; thou haſt kept me from many Deaths and Dangers; in the time of <hi>War</hi> thou didſt preſerve me from the Peril of the <hi>Bloody Sword;</hi> when I deſerved as much as any, to have been cut off the <hi>Land of the Living;</hi> thou haſt preſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me by <hi>Land</hi> and by <hi>Water,</hi> and in <hi>Forreign Parts,</hi> from many Evils that I have been ſubject to; thou haſt kept me in the Times of <hi>Centagion</hi> and <hi>Viſitation,</hi> from the <hi>Noyſom</hi> and <hi>Devouring Peſtilence,</hi> and other <hi>Diſtempers;</hi> many that lived with me, are gone to the <hi>Grave</hi> before me; and as they are <hi>dead,</hi> I am <hi>dying,</hi> not knowing what a <hi>Day</hi> may bring forth; my <hi>Breath</hi> is in my <hi>Noſtrils,</hi> and goes out every Moment, and whenſoever it ſhall be ſtopt, I muſt <hi>dye,</hi> and turn to <hi>duſt,</hi> then after <hi>Death</hi> there is no <hi>Repentance,</hi> this is the <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity</hi> of Life, the <hi>Day</hi> of <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Salvation,</hi> which if neglected, I can never have another; it is therefore of everlaſting Concernment to improve the preſent <hi>Opportunity,</hi> becauſe it is appointed for all Men and Women once to <hi>dye,</hi> and then to <hi>Judgment,</hi> and as <hi>Death</hi> leaves, <hi>Judgment</hi> will find, as the <hi>Tree</hi> falls, ſo it lies; there is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Deſire</hi> nor <hi>Invention</hi> in the <hi>Grave</hi> where I am going. O Lord, thou haſt been very merciful to preſerve me in the <hi>Calamities</hi> of Fire, and haſt wonderfully Protected and Provided for me ever ſince; and thou haſt been merciful to me indeed, to preſerve me againſt my <hi>own
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:105161:23"/>Will.</hi> I am a Living <hi>Monument</hi> of thy <hi>Mercies,</hi> a <hi>Brand</hi> ſnatcht out of the <hi>Burning Flame;</hi> thou haſt given me my Life for a <hi>Prey,</hi> and I have not lived to thy <hi>Praiſe;</hi> but like a <hi>Vile, Wretched, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>uworthy,</hi> and moſt <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngrateful Creature,</hi> I have ſinned againſt thee both in <hi>Thought, Word,</hi> and <hi>Deed.</hi> The Sins of my <hi>Thoughts</hi> have been more than I can think; thoſe of my <hi>Words,</hi> more than I am able to expreſs, and the Sins of my <hi>Deeds</hi> have been innumerable, my Life hath been an Act of open <hi>Rebellion</hi> againſt thee; I am guilty of Sins by <hi>Omiſſion, Commiſſion, Ignorance,</hi> and <hi>Wilful Diſobedience, Having left undone thoſe Things which I ought to have done, and committed thoſe Things whith I ought not to have done;</hi> I have ſinned againſt Heaven, Thee, my Relations, and againſt the <hi>Motions</hi> of thy Bleſſed Spirit, having made a Shew of <hi>Godlineſs;</hi> I have denyed the <hi>Power of it,</hi> and have called upon the <hi>Name</hi> of Chriſt, but have not departed from <hi>Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> I have given evil example unto others, by living con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rary to what I have Profeſſed, and have quenched and grieved the <hi>Mations</hi> of thy <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> which ſhould have ſealed me up unto the <hi>day of Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> I have <hi>Committed</hi> all <hi>Impieties</hi> with <hi>Greedineſs,</hi> and have ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravated my <hi>Tranſgreſſions</hi> with <hi>hanious Circumſtances;</hi> for I have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, not only againſt the <hi>Law,</hi> but againſt the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> not only <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly,</hi> but <hi>Wilfully</hi> and very <hi>preſumptiouſly</hi> againſt the Checks of my <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and the <hi>Light of Nature,</hi> inſomuch that my own <hi>Heart</hi> doth condemn me, and thou art greater, knowing all Things. I have abuſed thy <hi>Mercies,</hi> deſpiſed thy <hi>Judgments,</hi> and turned thy very <hi>Graces</hi> into <hi>Wantonneſs,</hi> inſomuch that my <hi>Iniquities</hi> are gone over my Head, and my Sins have covered me, I have nothing to plead for my ſelf, but <hi>Guilty, Guilty, Guilty</hi> of the Breach of all thy moſt <hi>Holy</hi> and <hi>Righteous Laws,</hi> I have forfited my Right to all that is Good, &amp; have made my ſelf liable to all <hi>Evils,</hi> both <hi>Temporal, Spiritual,</hi> and <hi>Eternal;</hi> it is even a Miracle of <hi>Mercy</hi> that I had not long ago been taken off in my Sin, and for my Sins, and have been made ſo <hi>Hellfull</hi> as I have been ſinful, and have had my Portion given me with <hi>Hyppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelievers,</hi> and thoſe that loveth, and maketh a <hi>Lye</hi> in that Lake which burns with <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Brimſtone,</hi> there to be tormented with <hi>Devils</hi> and <hi>Damned Spirits</hi> for evermore, that inſtead of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto thee, and calling on thy N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e in <hi>Mercy,</hi> I am not howling amongſt the <hi>Damn'd</hi> in an irrecoverable State that thy Patience is not ended toward me, and the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or of <hi>Grace</hi> ſhut everlaſtingly againſt me; thou mighteſt juſtly long ago have ſaid unto me, <hi>I would have healed thee, and thou wouldſt not: I would have Saved thy Soul,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:105161:24"/>but thou haſt deſpiſed my Salvation; I would have made thee happy, and thou haſt refuſed; therefore thou that art filthy, be filthy ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll, there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains no more Sacrifice for Sin, but a fearful looking for of Judgment, Fiery Indignation, and the Fierce Anger of the Lord, the Moſt Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God; therefore go thou Curſed into Everlaſting Fire, prepared for the Devils and their Angels.</hi> It had been but juſt with thee, O Lord, thus to have dealt by me, and thou mighteſt have Glorified thy <hi>Juſtice</hi> in my <hi>Juſt Condemnation,</hi> and <hi>Eternal Damnation;</hi> but there is <hi>Mercy</hi> with thee, that thou mayſt be feared, and thy tender <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> are over all thy Works, and <hi>Mercy</hi> pleaſeth thee; it is, becauſe thy <hi>Compaſſions</hi> fail not, that I am not conſumed. O what ſhall I ſay unto thee, thou <hi>Preſerver of Men?</hi> Whether ſhall I go, or to whom ſhall I fly? 'Tis thou alone that haſt the words of <hi>eternal Life,</hi> and there is n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Name</hi> under <hi>Heaven</hi> by whom I can be Saved, but by the <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> and 'tis againſt thee, <hi>O Father;</hi> thee, <hi>O Holy Jeſus;</hi> &amp; thee, <hi>O Holy</hi> &amp; <hi>Bleſſed Spirit;</hi> that I have ſin'd againſt the <hi>Holy</hi> and <hi>Bleſſed Trinity</hi> in <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> in <hi>Trinity. Jeſus Chriſt was wounded for my Tranſgreſſions, that by his Stripes I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> be healed;</hi> and I have wounded him afreſh by my Sins: <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Chaſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my Peace hath been upon his Shoulders, and he that knew no Sin, was made a Curſe unto Sin for me, that I might be made the Righteonſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God in him. He was pierced thorow with many Sorrows, and his precious Side was pierced with a Sphear, and his moſt precious Blood was ſpilt, that my Soul might be Eternally Saved, and I have pierced him again by my Sins. Jeſus was Crucified, and dyed the bitter and Curſed Death of the Croſs, that I might be Bleſſed and Everlaſtingly Saved, and I have Crucified the Lord of Life afreſh, &amp; have put him to open ſhame.</hi> O help me to look upon him whom I have pierced, and mourn over him, that I may be in bitterneſs of <hi>Spirit,</hi> and g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ieve becauſe I cannot grieve enough for my Sins, and becauſe I have grieved the <hi>Motions</hi> of thy <hi>Holy Spirit.</hi> Oh work in me a hatred of all ſin, which is the cauſe of all <hi>Evil,</hi> and help me to avoid the very <hi>Appearance</hi> of it: O Lord, thou haſt given ſome Encouragement for poor penitent Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to come unto thee, and graciouſly invited them, ſaying, <hi>Come unto me all ye that are weary and heavy Laden, and I will give you Reſt; ſeek, and ye ſhall find; knock, and it ſhall be opened unto you; call up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me in the Day of Trouble, and I will hear thee and deliver thee, and thou ſhalt glorifie me.</hi> Oh Lord, I come, I ſeek, I call, I cry, beſeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thee for <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> his ſake, to let me find reſt unto my Soul; <hi>Open unto me the Gates of Salvation, and be ye opened ye Everlaſting Gates, that the King of Glory may come in, and deliver me from the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:105161:24"/>Burthen of my Sins.</hi> Help me to Glorifie thee here, that I may be Glorified with thee to all Eternity: Lord, thou haſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed that, <hi>Thou wilt not break the Bruiſed Reed, nor quench the ſmoaking Flax, nor deſpiſe the day of ſmall Things:</hi> but haſt merciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtiled thy ſelf, <hi>to be a God hearing Prayers:</hi> and <hi>none of the Sons of</hi> Jacob <hi>ever ſought thy Face in vain.</hi> And thou haſt graciouſly decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thy ſelf to be, <hi>the Lord, Merciful, Gratious, of Patience, and great Goodneſs, who pardoneth Iniquity, Tranſgreſſions, and Sins, for thy own Names-ſake;</hi> and, <hi>thou deſireſt not the Death of a ſinner, but rather that he ſhould turn from his Wickedneſs and live:</hi> and haſt promiſed, <hi>That at what time ſoever a ſinner repenteth him of his ſin from the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom and ground of his Heart, thou wilt put away his Wickedneſs out of thy ſight, and remember his Tranſgreſſions no more.</hi> And it is a faithful Saying, worthy of all Acceptation, <hi>That Jeſus Chriſt came into the World to ſave ſinners,</hi> Of whom I am chief. O Lord, I Believe, help my Unbelief, help me to Believe, Repent, and Obey; for <hi>Jeſus</hi> ſake, have Mercy upon me, and work in me a godly Sorrow for my ſins, which may cauſe a true Repentance unto Salvation, never to be repented of; and for thy <hi>Names-ſake,</hi> pardon all my ſins; for thy Mercies-ſake do away my Iniquities; for thy Promiſe ſake do not remember my Tranſgreſſions any more. And for Jeſus Chriſt his ſake ſeal a free and a full Pardon of all my ſins unto my Soul. Say <hi>That thou art become my Salvation.</hi> And let the blood of Jeſus cleanſe me from all ſin. Oh this is a great Requeſt, I beg, who am unworthy of the leaſt Mercy; but I beg of thee for the ſake of Jeſus, he is thy Beloved Son in whom thou art well pleaſed, &amp; through whom thou canſt not be offended; he is my Saviour, and died to ſave me: accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the multitude of thy <hi>Compaſſions</hi> in the Lord Jeſus, deal with me in the pardoning of all my ſins; and let not ſin nor Satan whom thou hateſt, deſtroy the Work of thy hands, my <hi>Immortal Soul</hi> for whom Chriſt died; furniſh me with the <hi>Graces</hi> of thy <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> and give me <hi>Believing Grace and Mercy, Repenting Grace and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, Pardoning Grace and Mercy, Reſtraining Grace and Mercy, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting Grace and Mercy, Renewing Grace and Mercy,</hi> with <hi>Confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Grace and Mercy.</hi> Oh renew me in the Spirit of my Mind, help me to redeem time, becauſe I have miſpent much pretious time al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, and becauſe the days are evil, make me conſider the ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and uncertainty of my time; I have but a Moment to work for Eternity: e're long <hi>Death</hi> will come, and I ſhall be in a future ſtate then time will be no more; and many have been taken off in their, ſins, and for their ſins, that are now in an Eternal ſtate of Wo. O
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:105161:25"/>teach me in this my Day, to know the things that belong to my peace, before they are hid from mine Eyes; my day is already far ſpent, and my Night is at hand, I do not know what a Day may bring forth, let me not therefore any longer defer my <hi>Amendment</hi> of Life after ſo long a time; as it is called to day, help me to up, and be doing, and work while it is called to day, before the Night comes, when none works; help me to work out my <hi>Salvation</hi> with Fear and Trembling, and let me be very diligent to make my <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and Election ſure,</hi> the one thing needful, even the Salvation of my <hi>Immortal Soul,</hi> which is of everlaſting <hi>Concernment;</hi> that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I miſcarry in I may not be miſtaken in the great buſineſs of my <hi>Eternal Happineſs;</hi> to that end I moſt humbly pray thee again for <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi>'s ſake, to free me from the Power of all ſin, eſpecially, thoſe that my Nature is moſt prone to, ſuch as do beſet and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take me daily; and be pleaſed to diſcover unto me the Deceitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of my own Heart, which is very naughty, and above all things, deceitful and deſperately wicked, the Thoughts and Imaginations of my Heart have been evil, and only evil continually. O Lord, cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate in me a <hi>Clean</hi> and <hi>New Heart,</hi> renew a right <hi>Spirit</hi> within me, ſanctifie my <hi>Nature,</hi> and help me to ſanctifie thee, the Lord of <hi>Hoſts,</hi> and make thee my <hi>Fear</hi> and <hi>Dread,</hi> that thou may'ſt be unto me a <hi>Sanctuary;</hi> O be pleaſed to convince me of thine <hi>Omniſciency,</hi> and <hi>Omnipreſcency,</hi> ſtrike me with an Awe and Fear of thy Preſence; make me to conſider, that where-ever I am, &amp; whatever I am about, thou knoweſt it, who art a God of purer <hi>Eyes</hi> than to behold Sin with the leaſt Approbation, and that I have always about me an <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Soul,</hi> and that it is againſt thee that I have ſinned, who art a <hi>Sin-hating,</hi> and a <hi>Sin-revenging God,</hi> and that I muſt very ſhortly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear naked before thy dreadful <hi>Tribunal,</hi> to render an Account for all things done in the Fleſh, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ceive my Eternal <hi>Doom</hi> from the Righteous Judge of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll the World, O <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h me with the <hi>Robes of Chriſts Righteouſneſs,</hi> le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his Meritorious <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Paſſion</hi> ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie thy Juſtice for my Sins, let the Blood of J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>us cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anſe me from all ſin, and make me circumſpect in time to come, l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t me be <hi>Sober, Watchful,</hi> and <hi>Vigilant,</hi> becauſe my <hi>Aiverſary</hi> the Devil goeth about as a roaring Lion, ſeeking whom he may devour continually, and my poor, weak, fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>il Nature is ready to yield to every Temptation and Suggeſtion, not able to think a good Thought; O let thy <hi>Grace</hi> be ſufficient for me, let it ſhield me from all hurt, cloath me with the Righteouſneſs of my <hi>Jeſus,</hi> let me be girt with Truth, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:105161:25"/>ſhod with the Preparation of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> but above all things give me the Shield of Faith, the Breaſtplate of Righteouſneſs, a Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of Salvation, with the Sword of the Spirit, whereby I may be able to fight againſt the <hi>World,</hi> the <hi>Fleſh</hi> and the <hi>Devil,</hi> reſiſting the <hi>Fiery Darts</hi> of Satan, fighting againſt <hi>Principalities, Powers,</hi> and <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Wickedneſs</hi> in High-Places; let not the <hi>Gates of Hell,</hi> nor <hi>Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Darkneſs</hi> prevail againſt me; but let the <hi>Grace of God,</hi> which hath ſo plentifully appeared toward me, teaching to deny all <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs</hi> and <hi>Worldly Luſts,</hi> defend me; O let me be redeemed from a <hi>Vain Converſation,</hi> help me to bring forth fruits meet for <hi>Repentance,</hi> worthy an Amendment of Life, and let thy Holy Spirit ſeal me up unto the Day of <hi>Redemption,</hi> make me holy here, that I may be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py hereafter. Oh make me ſuch a one as thou wouldſt have me, and inable me to evidence unto my ſelf the Aſſurance of my Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication by the fruits of my Sanctification; thou haſt promiſed, <hi>That what ſoever ſhall be asked in thy Sons Name, according to thy Will, ſhall be granted.</hi> Now Lord, I know that this is thy Will, even my Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication; for Jeſus ſake, ſanctifie me thorowout, and write upon my Heart, <hi>Holineſs to the Lord,</hi> make me walk according to the Pattern of my Jeſus, who was <hi>Humble, Holy,</hi> and <hi>Obedient to thy Will</hi> in all things, even to the death of the <hi>Croſs;</hi> make me to conſider that I was Redeemed, and bought with a Price, not of corruptible Things, as <hi>Silver</hi> and <hi>Gold,</hi> but with the precious Blood of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let me live to the Praiſe of him that hath ſo dearly bought me with his moſt pretious Blood, let me walk like one that is Redeemed and Tranſlated from <hi>Death</hi> to <hi>Life,</hi> as one whoſe Life is hid with God in Chriſt, that when he who is my Life ſhall appear, I may alſo appear with him in <hi>Glory.</hi> O help me to walk as an Adopted Son of the mighty Majeſty of Heaven and Earth, the <hi>Holy God;</hi> as an Adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Brother to the <hi>Holy Jeſus,</hi> my <hi>Loving Saviour, Mighty Redeemer,</hi> and the <hi>Captain of my Salvation;</hi> as one that is in fellowſhip with <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>Holy Ghaſt,</hi> the <hi>Bleſſed Spirit, my Mighty Comforter, dayly Sanctifier and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reſerver,</hi> Oh help me to walk as one that is in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with, and related unto the moſt <hi>Holy</hi> and <hi>Bleſſed Trinity.</hi> Let me never turn to <hi>Folly</hi> more, nor dare to ſin any more, nor diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour my <hi>Heavenly Relations,</hi> but help me to walk worthy of the Price of my <hi>High-Calling,</hi> preſſing hard to the <hi>Mark,</hi> adorning my <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> walking in all <hi>Well-pleaſing,</hi> daily growing in <hi>Grace</hi> from <hi>ſtrength</hi> to <hi>ſtrength,</hi> til I ſhall appear in <hi>Zion</hi> in <hi>perfect beauty,</hi> in <hi>Glory</hi> make me to perſevere, be conſtant and faithful to the <hi>death,</hi> that ſo I
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:105161:26"/>may receive a Crown of Life, Righteouſneſs, and Glory that fadeth not away. To that end &amp; purpoſe, O God, wean me from the <hi>World;</hi> take off my Affections from all periſhing Vanities, make me <hi>Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Minded,</hi> whil'ſt I am about <hi>Earthly Buſineſs;</hi> let my Converſation be above, where the Lord <hi>Jeſus</hi> ſitteth at thy Right-hand, making Interceſſion for me; let me be in earneſt for thy <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Glory,</hi> and the Salvation of my <hi>Immortal Soul.</hi> O let me be upon the Wing Heavenward, and carry me on upon Divine Principles, help me to ſtrive to enter into the <hi>Streight Gate, Narrow is the Way that leads to Life and few there be that find it: Broad is the Way that leads to Deſtruction, and many there be that go in thereat;</hi> and if the <hi>Righteous</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hall ſcarce be Saved, where ſhall the <hi>Sinners</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly</hi> appear? Come <hi>Holy Ghoſt, Eternal God,</hi> Proceeding from the Father and Son, take Poſſeſſion of my Soul, throw down all the Strong-holds of Sin and Satan, bring me over unto a Univerſal Obedience in all Things to thy <hi>Heavenly Will.</hi> O that my <hi>Ways</hi> were directed to keep thy <hi>Commandments,</hi> then ſhall I not be aſhamed, when I have reſpect un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all thy <hi>Holy</hi> and moſt <hi>Righteous Laws,</hi> which are not grievous, as <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood,</hi> the <hi>World</hi> and <hi>Devils</hi> would perſwade me; thy <hi>Ways</hi> are <hi>Peace,</hi> thy <hi>Paths, Pleaſantneſs,</hi> in thy <hi>Preſence</hi> is <hi>Fulneſs of Joy,</hi> and at thy Right-hand are Rivers of <hi>Pleaſures</hi> for evermore then let it be the <hi>joy of my Heart,</hi> and <hi>rejoycing of my Soul</hi> to do <hi>thy Will,</hi> help me to hate the <hi>Garment</hi> that is ſpotted with the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> ſhed abroad a <hi>Divine Love</hi> into my <hi>Heart,</hi> and lay a <hi>Holy Conſtraint</hi> upon me to pleaſe thee in all Things. O make me conſider what great Things the Lord hath done for me, who was once a <hi>Child of Wrath,</hi> a <hi>Firebrand of Hell, Heir to Eternal Death and Damnation,</hi> but now by the Grace of God in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> am become an <hi>Heir</hi> to an <hi>Eternal and Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Kingdom;</hi> O let me be led unto it which way my <hi>Heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> pleaſeth, it being aſſured to me by the great <hi>Charter</hi> of <hi>Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precious Promiſes, ſealed by the Blood of Jeſus, the New Name, and the White Stone.</hi> O make me to know what the Lord hath done for my <hi>Soul</hi> and <hi>Body;</hi> my <hi>Soul</hi> is Redeemed from <hi>Hell,</hi> and my <hi>Body</hi> from the <hi>Grave,</hi> and both <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Soul</hi> from <hi>Eternal Damnation,</hi> and all by the Blood of my <hi>Jeſus;</hi> and my <hi>Vile Body</hi> ſhall be made a <hi>Glorious Body,</hi> and my <hi>Mortality</hi> ſhall put on <hi>Immortality,</hi> be ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up in Life, and I ſhall be a <hi>Co-heir</hi> with my <hi>Bleſſed Jeſus.</hi> O what ſhall I render unto the Lord for all his Benefits; help me to take the <hi>Cup of Salvation,</hi> and praiſe the Name of the Lord, let me ſpeak to thy Praiſe, and live to thy Praiſe, let my Heart be inlarged
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:105161:26"/>to ſhew it forth in my Generation, and let it be Matter of Eternal Praiſes in the Heavenly Quire, when I ſhall there be joyned with <hi>Saints, Angels, Arch-Angels, Cherubiens, Seraphims,</hi> the Spirits of Juſt <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Women</hi> made perfect, all the <hi>Heavenly</hi> and <hi>Celeſtial Hoſt</hi> to ſing <hi>Hallelujahs</hi> and a New Song unto thy <hi>Divine Majeſty,</hi> for thy Love in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> and in the mean time be pleaſed to accept of a <hi>Morning Sacrifice,</hi> which thy poor Creature doth deſire to offer up in Praiſe at this time, with all humble ſincerity, moſt earneſtly begging the Aſſiſtance of thy <hi>Grace:</hi> bleſſed be thy Name for keeping me all my Days for my <hi>Creation, Preſervation,</hi> and above all, for ever ever, ever; bleſſed be thy Name for the Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of all my Mercies, and through whom I have comfortable Hope and Aſſurance of Eternal Salvation. O let Chriſt be formed more and more in me, and bleſſed be thy Name for all Temporal Favours, for keeping me the Night paſt, for refreſhing me with the Comforts of Reſt and Sleep, and haſt kept me from all ſad Accidents, when thou mighteſt have made my Bed my Grave, and my Sleep my Death, but bleſſed be thy Name, whoſe Compaſſions never fail thy poor Creature, who haſt raiſed me this Morning in good Condition of Health, Strength, Mind, and Memory, and being thus brought to the beginning of this day, defend me, O Lord, in the ſame by thy Almighty Power, grant that I may fall into no Sin, nor run into any kind of Danger, but that all my Doings may be ordered by thy Governance, to do that which is righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous in thy Sight, through Jeſus Chriſt. O Lord have mercy upon thy whole Church, inlarge the Kingdom of <hi>Grace,</hi> haſten the Kingdom of <hi>Glory,</hi> ſend forth thy <hi>Word</hi> with thy <hi>Power</hi> thorow the whole <hi>World,</hi> propagate the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and haſten the Kingdom of Glory; remember thy Antient People, the <hi>Jews,</hi> bring in the Fulneſs of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> give the <hi>Heathen</hi> for thy Sons Inheritance, and the utmoſt Parts of the Earth for his Poſſeſſion, let all Kingdoms of the World become the Lord Chriſts, and let every Scepter ſubmit to his Royal Scepter, that the Earth may be filled with the Knowledge of the Lord, as the Waters cover the Sea: and be g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atiouſly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to bleſs this Sinful Nation of <hi>England,</hi> pardon our Crying Sins, heal our Breaches<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> compoſe our Differences, give us a true Repentance and Amendment of Life, and be merciful unto us. O Lord ſave the King, pour down the choiſeſt of thy Bleſſings upon his Head and Heart, make his Life long, &amp; his Reign proſperous, keep him from the hands of his Enemies, let his Life be prerious in thy Sight, give him Wiſdom and Courage from above, make him as an Angel of God, to go in and eut before the People over whom thou haſt ſet him, and when thou ſhalt put an end to his Mortal Life, Crown him in thy Everlaſting Kingdom in Glory, Bleſs him in his Royal Relations, our Gracious Queen <hi>Katherine, James</hi> Duke of <hi>York,</hi> and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Royal Family; endue them with thy holy Spirit, inrich them with thy Heavenly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, proſper them with all Happineſs, and bring them to thy Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Kingdom B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> to bleſs all our Privy-Councellors, Rulers, and Judges, teach our Senators Wiſdom, and the true Fear of the Lord, make them Zealous for thy Honour and Glory, the Advancement of true Religion, Piety and Vertue, the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:105161:27"/>Honour and Safety of the King and Kingdom. Bleſs all the Magiſtrates of this Realm, give them <hi>Grace</hi> to execute Juſtice and maintain Truth; and be pleaſed to pour down a double Portion of thy Bleſſings upon the Miniſters of thy Word and Sacraments, the Clergy of this Land, by what Names or Titles ſoever they are dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified or diſtinguiſhed, make them found in their Doctrine, and Exemplar in their Lives, let them ſhine like Stars in the Firmament, and let their Light ſo ſhine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſore Men, that ſeeing their good Works, others may glorifie thee, the Heavenly Father; and O Lord look down in much Mercy upon all Degrees of Men, Women, and Children of this Nation, grant that we may all live in thy Faith and Fear in due Obedieuce and Loyalty to the King and his Laws, and in Brotherly-Love and Affection to one another; O Lord, bleſs all my Relations, eſpecially my Wiſe and Child, pardon their Sins, and ſave their Souls, make them near and dear unto thy ſelf, ſeaſon their tender Years with thy <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Fear,</hi> be their ſatiable good in every Condition; and if it be thy bleſſed Will, bring us together again, that we may Serve thee better than ſormerly we have done; and if it ſhall ſeem good un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, O Lord, find out a way for my Deliverance out of Priſon, not mine, but thy Will be done, O God. I have found that thy Service is perfect Freedom, and thy Favour is better than Life: help me to order my Converſation aright, that I may ſee more of thy Salvation; let my ways pleaſe thee, that my Enemies may be at Peace with me; however, let all tend to the purging out of Sin, making me more fit to enjoy Communion with thee here, and eternally hereafter; vouchſafe, O Lord, to keep me this day without Sin, keep me in thy Fear, di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ert me in thy Truth, let thy Spirit lead me, that I may not offend with my Tongue, let me be ſilent rather than ſin, and never repine at thy Providence, fit me for my future Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, make me mindful of Death, and let me always have the Aſſurance of thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, which is better than Life. G God, whoſe Nature and Property is ever to have Mercy, and to forgive, receive my humble Petitions, and though I am tied and bound with the Chain of my Sin yet let the great pittifulneſs of thy Mercy looſe me, for the Honour of my Advocate and Mediator <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> to whom with thee, O Father, thy Holy and Bleſſed Spirit, be aſcrided and given from the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of my Heart, and from all Creatures, all poſſible Honour, Glory, Power, Praiſe. Might, Majeſty, Adoration, Dominion, and what-ever can be Imagined or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed from this time forth, and for evermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <hi>Our Father which art in Heaven: Hallowed be thy Name: Thy Kingdom come: Thy Will be done in Earth as it is in Heaven.</hi> &amp;c.</closer>
               <pb facs="tcp:105161:27"/>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
